<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog.atom"/>
  <title>Spore Life Sciences - Blog</title>
  <updated>2021-05-05T15:12:35-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Spore Life Sciences</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-long-does-it-take-mushrooms-to-work</id>
    <published>2021-05-05T15:12:35-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-05T15:12:35-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-long-does-it-take-mushrooms-to-work"/>
    <title>How Long Does It Take Mushrooms To Work?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>By: Dr. Michele Ross, PhD</strong></p>
<p>No, we’re not taking about those shrooms! Comparing the effects of psilocybin-containing magic mushrooms to medicinal mushrooms is like comparing apples to oranges. While the active ingredient in magic mushrooms makes users feel high or even hallucinate, medicinal mushrooms can improve energy, mood, and overall health, helping you feel your best. Medicinal mushrooms provide these health benefits from a multitude of active ingredients with anti-inflammatory, immune-boosting, and neuroprotective properties.<br><br>How you respond to functional mushrooms depends on many things, including which Spore mushroom blend you used. The effects may be subtle and build up over time or result in instant changes you can feel in an hour or less. Let’s dive into how it might feel to take each of the five Spore mushroom blends.<br><br><strong>When does Focus Performance blend start working?</strong><br>You may feel more alert and focused within an hour of taking this Spore mushroom blend. <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/focus-performance">Focus Performance</a> blend contains lion’s mane mushrooms, cordyceps mushrooms, ashwagandha, and ginkgo biloba. Gingko biloba may increase blood flow to the brain, providing tension relief and focus improvement within an hour. Ashwagandha is an adaptogen that helps lower stress hormone levels, and while you may see subtle results in an hour, consistent use will yield the best results. Same with the other ingredients including lion’s mane and cordyceps mushrooms, as they support brain health over time.<br><br><strong>When does Chill Out blend start working?</strong><br>If you’re highly stressed out, you should start feeling the effects of Chill Out blend rather quickly. <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/chill-out">Chill Out</a> blend contains reishi mushrooms and herbs including valerian root, passion flower, chamomile and lemon balm. These herbs promote relaxation, and effects can be felt within an hour. Some consumers use this blend at night to help promote a good night’s rest. If Chill Out blend makes you too sleepy during the day, you can try taking one capsule twice a day instead of both at the same time.<br><br><strong>When does Energy Performance blend start working?</strong><br><a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/energy-performance">Energy Performance</a> blend is one of our fastest acting formulas. It contains cordyceps and maitake mushrooms as well as panax ginseng, green tea extract, and guarana powder. This formula contains natural caffeine and will provide an instant burst of energy in less than an hour. The cordyceps mushrooms in this formula help you turn oxygen you breathe in into cellular energy more quickly, further boosting energy for hours without causing a crash like other supplements.<br><br><strong>When does Protect + Defend blend start working?</strong><br><a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/protect-defend">Protect + Defend</a> blend contains turkey tail, chaga, reishi and maitake mushrooms plus a blend of vitamins and minerals. This potent formula provides strong support for the immune system, helping you respond faster to microbes that come your way. To benefit the most from this mushroom blend, take it daily, and not just when you feel the symptoms of a cold or flu coming on. <br><br><strong>When does Mike’s Mushroom Mix start working?</strong><br>As a blend of 10 functional mushrooms, <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/mikes-mushroom-mix">Mike’s Mushroom Mix</a> is serving as a unique multivitamin that rebalances the immune system. Due to the anti-inflammatory nature of this mushroom blend, many consumers report feeling more energized, focused, and overall healthier after taking Mike’s Mushroom Mix for a month or two. <br><br><strong>Still don’t know if your mushrooms are working?</strong><br>Confused about which Spore mushroom blend is right for you? Or taking a Spore mushroom blend and not sure if it’s working? Join our <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/sporecommunity">Spore Mushroom Community</a> on Facebook to get support and ask Dr. Ross your questions about mushrooms and health. We’re here to support you on your wellness journey.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/controlling-an-overactive-thyroid</id>
    <published>2021-05-03T18:12:02-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-03T18:12:02-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/controlling-an-overactive-thyroid"/>
    <title>Controlling an Overactive Thyroid</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>by Jason S. Lupoi, Ph.D.</strong><br><br>The American Thyroid Association estimates that 20 million Americans have some type of thyroid disorder. Globally, this number reaches 200 million people. [1,2] Thyroid disease takes two paths: hypothyroidism or underactive thyroid where your body does not produce enough of specific hormones called T3 and T4; and hyperthyroidism or overactive thyroid, where your body produces too much of these hormones.<br><br>Both types of thyroid disease are more common in women than in men. Of those diagnosed with thyroid disease, approximately 99% are affected by hypothyroidism. [3] The most common cause of the less frequent hyperthyroidism is Graves’ disease, where antibodies attack the thyroid gland causing it to produce too much T3 and T4. <br><br><strong>Symptoms of Hyperthyroidism</strong><br><br>Hyperthyroidism presents several symptoms, such as nervousness, mood swings, irritability, weight loss, rapid heart rate, excessive sweating, bulging eyes, and difficulty sleeping. Left untreated, an overactive thyroid can result in blood clots, stroke, heart failure, osteoporosis, and an overall decreased quality of life, mirroring symptoms of depression.</p>
<p><strong>Treating Hyperthyroidism </strong><br><br>There are various methods to treat hyperthyroidism. For example, the ingestion of radioactive iodine can shrink your thyroid gland and is thought to be the best-known to cure hyperthyroidism, often after as little as one dose. [4] Anti-thyroid medications can prevent your thyroid gland from producing too much T3 and T4. Some of these drugs, however, can cause liver problems, which in severe cases can result in death. Symptoms of hyperthyroidism, such as a racing heart, can be controlled with beta blockers, which are drugs typically used to treat high blood pressure. In more severe cases, a thyroidectomy may be required, where a substantial portion of the thyroid gland is removed.</p>
<p>Since Graves’ disease can affect one’s eyes, causing pain, inflammation, and sensitivity to light and wind, having access to and using artificial tears or topical products that provide anti-inflammatory properties can also provide relief.<br><br><strong><br>Mitigating the Effects of Hyperthyroidism Through Lifestyle Changes</strong><br><br>On the bright side, there are several natural ways to control hyperthyroidism too, primarily by altering one’s everyday lifestyle. One example is to avoid foods that contain iodine, such as seaweed, shrimp, fish, milk, cheese, and iodized salt. As well, because hyperthyroidism can lead to osteoporosis, taking Vitamin D and calcium supplements can help bolster your bones.<br><br>As with many medical conditions, getting appropriate cardiovascular exercise can help maximize muscle tone and increase your energy. Because bone density loss can occur with hyperthyroidism [5], resistance or strength training is recommended since it helps maintain bone density [6] and the recovery of skeletal muscle function [7]. Also, hyperthyroidism causes nervousness, anxiety, and irritability, and finding ways to relax can be vital to help reduce the impact of hyperthyroidism.<br> <br><strong>How Mushrooms Can Help </strong><br><br>Through various studies, cordyceps mushrooms have been evaluated for treating Graves’ disease. [8] Of the 44 sufferers of the disease that participated in one study, 28 were given cordyceps mushrooms. The researchers found that the mushrooms helped restore the balance of helper and cytotoxic T cells, both integral to our body’s immune responses.<br> <br>Other mushrooms help support the gut microbiome, which in turn, can provide support for thyroid function, since thyroid and intestinal conditions often coexist. [9] A diet supplemented with shiitake mushrooms led to alterations in gut microbiota when tested on rats which were fed the mushrooms over 42 days. [10] Consumption of the mushrooms increased the abundance of Clostridium <br>and Bacteroides microbes that play pivotal roles in regulating gut health. [11] <br><br>Chaga mushrooms can also help support gut health, and one study evaluated the effects of chaga mushrooms on patients suffering from inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD) like ulcerative colitis and Crohn’s disease, both of often coexist with thyroid dysfunction. [12,13] IBD is thought to be partially caused by oxidative stress from free radicals that induce inflammation. The chaga mushrooms provided antioxidative properties, protecting the gut from oxidative stress.<br><br>There are several everyday ways to better control hyperthyroidism, starting with your diet, and ensuring that you are consuming foods and supplements that do not aggravate the condition. Mushrooms like cordyceps, shiitake, and chaga, all of which are in Spore Life Sciences Mike’s Mushroom Mix, have demonstrated their ability to boost gut health and immune responses, two integral pathways to quell the symptoms of hyperthyroidism.<br><br><strong>References</strong><br>[1] American Thyroid Association. General information/press room. Accessed April 8, 2021.<br>[2] Siemens Healthineers. Women and thyroid disease. Accessed April 8, 2021.<br>[3] Chiovato L, Magri F, Carlé A. Hypothyroidism in context: Where we've been and where we're going. Adv Ther. 2019;36(Suppl 2):47-58. <br>[4] Michigan Medicine – University of Michigan. Radioactive iodine for hyperthyroidism. Accessed April 8, 2021.<br>[5] Tuchendler D, Bolanowski M. The influence of thyroid dysfunction on bone metabolism. Thyroid Res. 2014;7(1):12. <br>[6] Hong AR, Kim SW. Effects of resistance exercise on bone health. Endocrinol Metab (Seoul). 2018;33(4):435-444. <br>[7] Bousquet-Santos K, Vaisman M, Barreto ND, et al. Resistance training improves muscle function and body composition in patients with hyperthyroidism. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2006;87(8):1123-1130.<br>[8] He T, Zhao R, Lu Y, et al. Dual-directional immunomodulatory effects of Corbrin capsule on autoimmune thyroid diseases. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2016;2016:1360386. <br>[9] Knezevic J, Starchl C, Tmava Berisha A, Amrein K. Thyroid-gut-axis: How does the microbiota influence thyroid function?. Nutrients. 2020;12(6):1769. <br>[10] Anwar H, Suchodolski JS, Ullah MI, et al. Shiitake culinary-medicinal mushroom, Lentinus edodes (Agaricomycetes), supplementation alters gut microbiome and corrects dyslipidemia in rats. Int J Med Mushrooms. 2019;21(1):79-88.<br>[11] Lopetuso LR, Scaldaferri F, Petito V, Gasbarrini A. Commensal Clostridia: leading players in the maintenance of gut homeostasis. Gut Pathog. 2013;5(1):23. <br>[12] Najafzadeh M, Reynolds PD, Baumgartner A, Jerwood D, Anderson D. Chaga mushroom extract inhibits oxidative DNA damage in lymphocytes of patients with inflammatory bowel disease. Biofactors. 2007;31(3-4):191-200.<br>[13] Shizuma T. Concomitant thyroid disorders and inflammatory bowel disease: A literature review. Biomed Res Int. 2016;2016:5187061. <br><br></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-to-defog-your-brain</id>
    <published>2021-04-26T17:13:24-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-26T17:13:24-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-to-defog-your-brain"/>
    <title>How to Defog Your Brain</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>by Jason S. Lupoi, Ph.D.</strong><br><br>Modern living comes with many distractions that can hinder our ability to pay attention, focus, think clearly, or break through the daily brain fog. Brain fog can result from stress, a lack of sleep, a poor diet, medications, or medical conditions, and can take its toll on our work and personal lives.<br><br>Our modern lives would feel rather naked without our smartphones wouldn’t they? But smartphones can also lead to brain fog as well. One study postulated that “habitual involvement with these devices may have a negative and lasting impact on users’ ability to think, remember, pay attention, and regulate emotion.” [1] The study reports that “considerable evidence implicates smartphone technology as a source of sleep disturbances, with a compound effect on cognitive functioning and work engagement the following day.”<br><br>Therefore, finding ways to harness and improve your focus, and sustain that mental clarity once its recovered, is paramount to leading a more productive work and personal life. Thankfully, there are several natural ways that can boost your mental clarity.<br><br>Lion’s mane mushrooms and the polysaccharides within them can promote neuronal health, and animal models have shown that these polysaccharides can stimulate the production of nerve growth factor (a protein that’s involved in neuronal growth, proliferation, maintenance, and survival) in the hippocampus, a region of the brain involved in memory and learning. [2]<br><br>The tree called Gingko biloba serves as another example of a botanical product marketed for its ability to augment mental clarity and focus. While more research may need to be done to validate the claims, one clinical trial conducted on 262 people aged 60 or older showed improved cognitive abilities in the group who ingested Gingko biloba versus the placebo group. [3] What’s more, Gingko biloba may help alleviate anxiety. While the “more research needs to be done” mantra applies here as well, one study of 170 people showed that those given 480 mg of Gingko biloba reported a 45% reduction in anxiety. [4] Less anxiety means less stress, and less stress may translate to better mental clarity.<br><br>There are other simple ways to treat brain fog. For example, you may not be getting enough sleep, so ensure that you allow for adequate rest. And as always, exercising regularly can also help sharpen the mind. Pairing that with a supplement designed to improve focus, such as Spore Life Science’s Focus Performance formulation, containing lion’s mane mushrooms and Gingko biloba, should get you well on your way to clearing your mind and living life to the fullest.<br><br><strong>References</strong><br>[1] Wilmer HH, Sherman LE, Chein JM. Smartphones and cognition: a review of research exploring the links between mobile technology habits and cognitive functioning. Front Psychol. 2017;8:605.<br>[2] Mori K, Obara Y, Hirota M, et al. Nerve growth factor-inducing activity of Hericium erinaceus in 1321N1 human astrocytoma cells. Biol Pharm Bull. 2008;31(9):1727-1732.<br>[3] Mix JA, Crews WD Jr. A double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomized trial of Ginkgo biloba extract EGb 761 in a sample of cognitively intact older adults: neuropsychological findings. Hum Psychopharmacol. 2002;17(6):267-277.<br>[4] Woelk H, Arnoldt KH, Kieser M, Hoerr R. Ginkgo biloba special extract EGb 761 in generalized anxiety disorder and adjustment disorder with anxious mood: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. J Psychiatr Res. 2007;41(6):472-480.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-ways-medicinal-mushrooms-fight-aging</id>
    <published>2021-04-19T12:43:37-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-19T12:43:37-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-ways-medicinal-mushrooms-fight-aging"/>
    <title>Five Ways Medicinal Mushrooms Fight Aging</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Mushrooms may not be the first ingredient that comes to mind when it comes to ingredients that fight wrinkles, boost memory, and even extend your life span. We’re not talking about the mushrooms on your pizza. Medicinal mushrooms including lion’s mane mushrooms and less known ones like antrodia mushrooms are the hot new ingredient in many beauty and health products.<br><br>Here are five medicinal mushrooms you should be using to fight aging:<br><br><strong>1. Antrodia Mushrooms</strong><br>Antrodia shows great promise as an ingredient in wrinkle creams or facial sunscreens. When applied topically to the skin, antrodia can reduce inflammation, breakdown of collagen in the skin, and water loss in skin exposed to the sun. [1] Antrodia can also be taken as a supplement, and has been used in Chinese medicine for fighting many types of cancer including lung, liver, and breast cancer. [2,3]<br><br><strong>2. Reishi Mushrooms</strong><br>Known as the “Queen of mushrooms” reishi can be applied to the skin topically or eaten as a supplement. Reishi skincare products are full of antioxidants including ergothioneine and glutathione that stop free radial formation and prevent premature aging from sun exposure. <br><br>Reishi has another nickname, the “mushroom of immortality,” and for good reason. Reishi is known to increase the length of your lifespan, as well as the quality of life in your senior years. Reishi contains many unique chemicals including polysaccharides and triterpenes that protect your DNA from oxidative stress, preventing aging and cancer. [4] Reishi even turns on the gene called daf-16 that increases lifespan in species from worms to humans. [5]<br><br><strong>3. Lion’s Mane Mushrooms</strong><br>Lion’s mane is world-renowned for its effects on the brain and its ability to boost cognitive function in seniors. Two chemicals in lion’s mane, erinacines and hericenones, boost production of nerve growth factor (NGF) in the brain, which boosts brain cell growth and repair. Numerous polysaccharides and triterpenes in lion’s mane improve memory and even motor function in aging mice. [6]<br><br><strong>4. Cordyceps Mushrooms</strong><br>Cordyceps mushroom is revered in Chinese medicine as an anti-aging herb. It contains numerous chemicals that act as antioxidants and anti-inflammatories, which keep the brain healthy as it ages. Cordyceps reduces oxidative stress in the brain and improves memory [7]. These mushrooms also improve the way the body and brain use oxygen during exercise, which can help you stay fit and mobile as you get older. [8,9]<br><br><strong>5. King Trumpet Mushrooms</strong><br>King trumpet mushrooms are also known as king oyster mushrooms, and are a great addition to soups, pastas, and even salads. King trumpets can also be taken as a dietary supplement in the form of powders and capsules. They contain a protein called PEP that reduces inflammation and growth of colon cancer cells. [10,11]<br><br>King Trumpet are also full of ergothioneine, a master antioxidant that can fight free radical damage and oxidative stress, making it a potent mushroom for fighting aging and inflammation. While all mushrooms, including white button mushrooms, have some levels of ergothioneine, king trumpet mushrooms have much higher levels than other varieties. <br><br><strong>Conclusion</strong><br>Mushrooms are an amazing way to fight aging. To get the full health benefits of medicinal mushrooms like lion’s mane and reishi, it’s best to use a supplement like Spore’s Mike’s Mushroom Mix that includes ten of the most powerful medicinal mushrooms.<br><br><strong>References</strong><br>1. Kuo YH, Lin TY, You YJ, Wen KC, Sung PJ, Chiang HM. Antiinflammatory and Antiphotodamaging Effects of Ergostatrien-3β-ol, Isolated from Antrodia camphorata, on Hairless Mouse Skin. Molecules. 2016 Sep 10;21(9):1213.<br>2. Long, Huei; Hu, Chi-Tan; Prijatelj, Vesna Weng, Ching-Feng. Antrodia cinnamomea is a potentially effective complementary medicine for adjuvant therapy against breast cancer with bone metastasis, Medicine: July 02, 2020 - Volume 99 - Issue 27.<br>3. Huang, TT., Lan, YW., Chen, CM. et al. Antrodia cinnamomea induces anti-tumor activity by inhibiting the STAT3 signaling pathway in lung cancer cells. Sci Rep 2019;9:5145.<br>4. Wang J, Cao B, Zhao H, Feng J. Emerging Roles of Ganoderma Lucidum in Anti-Aging. Aging Dis. 2017;8(6):691-707. <br>5. Chuang MH, Chiou SH, Huang CH, Yang WB, Wong CH. The lifespan-promoting effect of acetic acid and Reishi polysaccharide. Bioorg Med Chem. 2009 Nov 15;17(22):7831-40.<br>6. Ratto D, Corana F, Mannucci B, et al. Hericium erinaceus Improves Recognition Memory and Induces Hippocampal and Cerebellar Neurogenesis in Frail Mice during Aging. Nutrients. 2019;11(4):715.<br>7. Ji DB, Ye J, Li CL, Wang YH, Zhao J, Cai SQ. Antiaging effect of Cordyceps sinensis extract. Phytother Res. 2009 Jan;23(1):116-22. <br>8. Hirsch KR, Smith-Ryan AE, Roelofs EJ, Trexler ET, Mock MG. Cordyceps militaris Improves Tolerance to High-Intensity Exercise After Acute and Chronic Supplementation. J Diet Suppl. 2017;14(1):42-53.<br>9. Yi, X., Xi-zhen, H. &amp; Jia-shi, Z. Randomized double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial and assessment of fermentation product of Cordyceps sinensis (Cs-4) in enhancing aerobic capacity and respiratory function of the healthy elderly volunteers. Chin. J. Integr. Med. 2004;10:187–192.<br>10. Yuan B., Ma N., Zhao L., Zhao E., Gao Z., Wang W., Song M., Zhang G., Hu Q., Xiao H. (2017). In Vitro and In Vivo Inhbitory Effects of a Pleurotus eryngii Protein on Colon Cancer Cells. Food and Function. 10.<br>11. H Q., Yuan B., Xiao H., Zhao L. Wu X., Rakariyatham K., Zhong L., Han Y., Muinde Kimatu B., Yang W. (2018). Polyphenols-Rich Extract From Pleurotus eryngii with Growth Inhibitoru of HCT116 Colon Cancer Cells and Anti-Inflammatory Function in RAW264.7 Cells. Food and Function. 9(3): 1601–1611.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-ways-functional-mushrooms-support-healthy-weight-loss</id>
    <published>2021-04-12T12:08:32-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-12T12:08:32-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-ways-functional-mushrooms-support-healthy-weight-loss"/>
    <title>Five Ways Functional Mushrooms Support Healthy Weight Loss</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>By: Dr. Michele Ross, PhD</strong></p>
<p>Weight gain is something we’ve all struggled with, but for many people, it has been harder than ever this year to lose the pounds. A recent study found that over 40% of Americans gained weight during the COVID pandemic lockdown and put on average of 29 pounds. [1] Many people are looking for fast ways to shed the pounds without having to go to gyms or other public places where they might be exposed to the virus. One of the easiest ways to lose weight and keep it off is by changing your diet.<br><br>The old saying “let food be thy medicine” should be your go-to line when it comes to weight loss. But which food? You might be surprised that mushrooms are a food packed with active ingredients that support metabolism and healthy eating habits. This isn’t just based on anecdotal evidence; most medicinal mushrooms have been deeply researched by scientists due to their use in ancient medicine.<br><br>From regular white button mushrooms to exotic functional mushrooms like lion’s mane, reishi, and chaga, you have many ways to incorporate mushrooms in your diet and exercise program. While some people cook functional mushrooms like lion’s mane and add them to pasta or eat them like burgers, you can get immense benefits by taking them in capsule form as a supplement.<br><br>Here are five health benefits of functional mushrooms for weight loss:<br><br><strong>1. Stop Stress-Eating</strong><br>A lot of people cope with stress by eating junk food, their favorite comfort food, or a calorie-heavy bottle of wine. Even if you’re consciously trying to avoid junk food, it’s super easy to fall off the health food wagon and relapse into stress eating. Thankfully, several functional mushrooms contain compounds that ease stress and reduce symptoms of anxiety. <br><br>Research studies have found several compounds in lion’s mane mushrooms, including erinacine A and amycenone, that have anti-anxiety and antidepressant like effects in mice. [2, 3] Reishi mushroom is also known for its mood lifting properties as proven in studies on mice. [4] By consuming functional mushrooms, you may feel more relaxed and reduce mindless eating as well as cravings for high-fat, high-sugar, and high-salt foods. <br><br><strong>2. Boost Fat Metabolism</strong><br>Most people think about benefits for the immune system or the brain when they think about medicinal mushrooms. What they don’t realize is that mushrooms can have amazing potential to treat obesity and reduce the harm from unhealthy diet and lifestyle habits. When mice were given lion’s mane extract for a month along with a high fat diet, they gained less body weight and fat. [5] Reishi mushrooms given to mice fed a high fat diet for a month had a similar effect of reducing body weight and fat gain. [6] Additionally, mice fed reishi also had lower levels of inflammation, suggesting they were healthier all around.<br><br><strong>3. Reduce Fatigue</strong><br>One of the main excuses people have for not exercising is that they are too tired after a long day of work. And if even if they do have the energy to get to the gym or start that yoga class online, they fizzle out and stop in the middle of their session and don’t get the full benefits. Taking medicinal mushrooms that boost energy can help you start exercising and extend the length or intensity of your cardio session. Cordyceps mushroom is the go-to mushroom for people who are tired, as it increases your body’s ability to turn oxygen into energy and increases athletic performance. [7,8] Reishi mushroom has also been heavily researched for its ability to improve energy and quality of life in patients with chronic illness such as breast cancer and nerve pain. [9,10] <br><br><br><strong>4. Level Blood Sugar</strong><br>Reishi mushroom, known as the “Queen of Mushrooms,” is known for its ability to balance blood sugar, which can stop food cravings and weight gain. The polysaccharides in reishi mushroom may help sensitize insulin receptors in the pancreas so that they respond better to insulin release after meals. While some studies suggest reishi mushroom is effective for leveling blood sugar in patients with type 2 diabetes, it is unclear whether it does the same thing for patients without diabetes. [11] Lion’s mane mushroom is also amazing for lower blood sugar in both normal and diabetic mice, and it does so by blocking enzymes that break down carbohydrates in the gut. [12,13]<br><br><strong>5. Reduce Hunger</strong><br>If you choose to eat your mushrooms whole instead of using mushroom supplements in powder or capsule form, you’ll get even more health benefits when it comes to weight loss. Mushrooms are chock full of beta-glucan fiber that helps your stomach feel full and reduce appetite. As a bonus, mushrooms also contain mevinolin, an enzyme that inhibits cholesterol production and is now prescribed as the prescription drug Lovastatin. [14] Mushrooms are also a great source of protein that doesn’t come from animals, making it a great choice for vegetarians and vegans. Meals that are high in protein tend to reduce hunger for more hours than meals high in carbohydrates, like pasta and bread.<br><br><strong>Conclusion</strong><br>Mushrooms can be a powerful tool in your weight loss journey. Try swapping meat for mushrooms for one to two meals a week to cut down on calories and reap the benefits of the fiber, vitamins, and beta-glucans in mushrooms. To get the full health benefits of functional mushrooms like lion’s mane or reishi, it’s best to use a supplement like <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/mikes-mushroom-mix">Mike’s Mushroom Mix</a> from Spore that includes ten of the most powerful medicinal mushrooms.<br><br><strong>References</strong><br>1. American Psychological Association, “Stress in America” pandemic survey https://www.apa.org/news/press/releases/stress/2021/data-charts-march-weight-change<br>2. Chiu CH, Chyau CC, Chen CC, Lee LY, Chen WP, Liu JL, Lin WH, Mong MC. Erinacine A-Enriched Hericium erinaceus Mycelium Produces Antidepressant-Like Effects through Modulating BDNF/PI3K/Akt/GSK-3β Signaling in Mice. Int J Mol Sci. 2018 Jan 24;19(2):341.<br>3. Yao W, Zhang JC, Dong C, Zhuang C, Hirota S, Inanaga K, Hashimoto K. Effects of amycenone on serum levels of tumor necrosis factor-α, interleukin-10, and depression-like behavior in mice after lipopolysaccharide administration. Pharmacol Biochem Behav. 2015 Sep;136:7-12.<br>4. Matsuzaki H, Shimizu Y, Iwata N, Kamiuchi S, Suzuki F, Iizuka H, Hibino Y, Okazaki M. Antidepressant-like effects of a water-soluble extract from the culture medium of Ganoderma lucidum mycelia in rats. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2013 Dec 26;13:370. <br>5. Hiwatashi K, Kosaka Y, Suzuki N, Hata K, Mukaiyama T, Sakamoto K, Shirakawa H, Komai M. Yamabushitake mushroom (Hericium erinaceus) improved lipid metabolism in mice fed a high-fat diet. Biosci Biotechnol Biochem. 2010;74(7):1447-51.<br>6. Chen Diling, Guo Yinrui, Qi Longkai, Tang Xiaocui, Liu Yadi, Feng Jiaxin, Zhu Xiangxiang, Zeng Miao, Shuai Ou, Wang Dongdong, Xie Yizhen, Burton B. Yang, Wu Qingping. Metabolic regulation of Ganoderma lucidum extracts in high sugar and fat diet-induced obese mice by regulating the gut-brain axis. Journal of Functional Foods. 2020,65:103639.<br>7. Hirsch KR, Smith-Ryan AE, Roelofs EJ, Trexler ET, Mock MG. Cordyceps militaris Improves Tolerance to High-Intensity Exercise After Acute and Chronic Supplementation. J Diet Suppl. 2017;14(1):42-53.<br>8. Yi, X., Xi-zhen, H. &amp; Jia-shi, Z. Randomized double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial and assessment of fermentation product of Cordyceps sinensis (Cs-4) in enhancing aerobic capacity and respiratory function of the healthy elderly volunteers. Chin. J. Integr. Med. 2004;10:187–192.<br>9. Zhao H, Zhang Q, Zhao L, Huang X, Wang J, Kang X. Spore Powder of Ganoderma lucidum Improves Cancer-Related Fatigue in Breast Cancer Patients Undergoing Endocrine Therapy: A Pilot Clinical Trial. Evid Based Complement Alternat Med. 2012;2012:809614.<br>10. Tang W, Gao Y, Chen G, Gao H, Dai X, Ye J, Chan E, Huang M, Zhou S. A randomized, double-blind and placebo-controlled study of a Ganoderma lucidum polysaccharide extract in neurasthenia. J Med Food. 2005 Spring;8(1):53-8. <br>11. Gao, Yihuai &amp; Lan, Jin &amp; Dai, Xihu &amp; Ye, Jingxian &amp; Zhou, Shufeng. A Phase I/II Study of Ling Zhi Mushroom Ganoderma lucidum (W.Curt.:Fr.)Lloyd (Aphyllophoromycetideae) Extract in Patients with Type II Diabetes Mellitus. International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms. 2004;6. 33-40. <br>12. Liang B, Guo Z, Xie F, Zhao A. Antihyperglycemic and antihyperlipidemic activities of aqueous extract of Hericium erinaceus in experimental diabetic rats. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2013;13:253. <br>13. He X, Wang X, Fang J, Chang Y, Ning N, Guo H, Huang L, Huang X, Zhao Z. Structures, biological activities, and industrial applications of the polysaccharides from Hericium erinaceus (Lion's Mane) mushroom: A review. Int J Biol Macromol. 2017 Apr;97:228-237. <br>14. McCune SA, Jurin RR. Effect of mevinolin on cholesterol metabolism in obese and lean Zucker rats. Biochem Pharmacol. 1987 Mar 15;36(6):875-9. </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/why-men-have-a-weaker-immune-system-than-women</id>
    <published>2021-04-05T14:35:44-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-05T14:35:44-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/why-men-have-a-weaker-immune-system-than-women"/>
    <title>Why Men Have A Weaker Immune System Than Women</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<strong>Dr. Michele Ross, PhD</strong><br><br>Men and women differ by gender in a lot of physiological differences, from body fat to height, hormones and lifespan. One big difference between the sexes that might surprise you is how the immune system functions in women versus men. So how did men up end up with a weaker immune system than women?<br><br><strong>Women Have Stronger Mast Cells</strong><br>Mast cells are immune system cells that recognize specific proteins on pathogens like viruses and bacteria and cause inflammation when activated. Unfortunately, mast cells can also react to foods, medications, stress, heat, and even strong smells. Mast cells are responsible for allergic reactions and food sensitives. Prolonged activation of mast cells can result in conditions like leaky gut, chronic rashes, headaches, and gut pain.<br><br>Women have over 4,000 genes that more active in their mast cells than men. [1] Women are more likely to have oversensitive and hyperactive mast cells, leading to higher rates of allergies and autoimmune disorders. Because stress can hyperactivate mast cells, it’s important for women to lower their stress levels. Spore’s <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/chill-out">Chill Out Blend</a> contains reishi mushroom and other botanical ingredients that support relaxation.<br><br><strong>X Marks The Spot</strong><br>Women have two copies of the X chromosome and men only have one. The X chromosome contains strains of ribonucleic acid called microRNAs, and it’s estimated that ten percent of all microRNAs are on that gene. Many microRNAs have been found to regulate genes for the immune system. Women likely have a more robust immune system than men because more of the genes for the immune system are turned on. [2]<br><br><strong>Women Live Longer</strong><br>According to the World Health Organization (WHO), women live six to eight years longer than men in most countries. Because women have stronger immune systems, they are in a better position to fight off pathogens like bacteria, viruses, and mold. Interestingly, women are also two to five times less likely to have cancer than men, and this is because our immune system is our first defense against small cancer cells growing into tumors.<br><br><strong>Women Have More Autoimmune Diseases</strong><br>Having a stronger immune system than men isn’t always a plus for women. Women have a higher rate of autoimmune disorders like lupus or irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), which happen when the immune system attacks the body instead of pathogens. Women also are more likely to have health conditions where the immune system plays a role, including allergies and migraines.<br><br><strong>Women Have More Severe Reactions to Vaccines</strong><br>Because women have a more robust immune system, they respond more strongly to vaccinations. This includes things like measles, hepatitis B, the flu, and even the new COVID-19 vaccines. With the new COVID vaccines, women are more likely to report more severe and longer lasting side effects like fever, headache, fatigue, and pain than men. Women even account for 80 percent of all allergic reactions to all vaccines. [3] <br><br><strong>Conclusion</strong><br>Whether you’re a man or a woman, it is still important to support a healthy immune system. Mushrooms can both boost the immune system when it’s suppressed or suppress an overactive immune system in the case of autoimmune diseases. One way to easily balance your immune system is with Spore’s <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/protect-defend">Protect &amp; Defend Blend</a>, which contains turkey tail, reishi, maitake, and chaga mushrooms, and other all-natural ingredients. <br><br><br><strong>References</strong><br>1. Mackey, E., Ayyadurai, S., Pohl, C.S. et al. Sexual dimorphism in the mast cell transcriptome and the pathophysiological responses to immunological and psychological stress. Biol Sex Differ 2016;7:60.<br>2. Pinheiro, I., Dejager, L. and Libert, C. (2011), X‐chromosome‐located microRNAs in immunity: Might they explain male/female differences? Bioessays, 33: 791-802.<br>3. Su JR, Moro PL, Ng CS, Lewis PW, Said MA, Cano MV. Anaphylaxis after vaccination reported to the Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System, 1990-2016. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2019;143(4):1465-1473. <br><br>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-medicinal-mushrooms-help-fight-cancer</id>
    <published>2021-03-29T12:05:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-03-29T12:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-medicinal-mushrooms-help-fight-cancer"/>
    <title>How Medicinal Mushrooms Help Fight Cancer</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><b>By:</b> <b>Dr.</b><b> Jason S. </b><b>Lupoi</b><b>, </b><b>Ph.D.</b></p>
<p>Unfortunately, you’d be hard pressed to find anyone that hasn’t been touched by cancer in some way or another. There is a deep need for therapeutic options that can be readily utilized to inhibit Cancer cells.</p>
<p>Fungi may have effective anticancer properties, and the properties that medicinal or functional mushrooms provide demonstrate the fungi’s impressive potential. One can simply visit Semantic Scholar and search for keywords like “mushrooms” and “anticancer” and find thousands of results.</p>
<p>Reishi mushrooms are one ancient example of a medicinal mushroom, as they are mentioned in the Chinese text Shen Nung Ben Cao Jing (The Classic of Herbal Medicine), thought to be written between 200 and 250 CE. [1] A vigorous immune system is vital in cancer treatment, and reishi mushroom polysaccharides and triterpenes stimulate cancer resistance through their immune-enhancing capabilities. This activity may be caused by inducing apoptosis (cell death) of cancerous cells or through their ability to boost immune response activity. [2,3] Reishi triterpenes, such as ganoderenic acid B, offer anti-cancer properties as well, through their toxicity to cancer cells, anti-metastatic effects, and induction of apoptosis. [4, 5]</p>
<p>Other mushrooms offer anticancer properties as well. An α-glucan from maitake mushrooms offers anti-tumor activity by promoting the production of cells that enhance our immune systems like tumor necrosis factor α, different interleukins, and through macrophage cell activation. [6] Another polysaccharide called maitake Z-fraction (MZF) also inhibited tumor growth in a preclinical model of colon cancer. [7]</p>
<p>Chaga mushrooms contain compounds such as 3β-hydroxy-lanosta-8,24-dien-21-al, inotodiol (a triterpene), and lanosterol, and each of these molecules showed effectiveness against lung, stomach, breast, and cervical cancer cell lines with low toxicity to normal cells. [8] These researchers first extracted the mushrooms, and subsequently purified multiple fractions that contained different phytochemicals. While all fractions had cytotoxic activity against the cancer cells, doses of 100 and 200 micrograms of one of the fractions reduced tumor volume by 24% and 34%, respectively. Molecules extracted from chaga using hot water have also shown anticancer properties against human colon cancer cells. [9]</p>
<p>The polysaccharide called krestin, or PSK in turkey tail mushrooms has also shown powerful anticancer properties, with one study measuring an increased survival in colon cancer patients who received PSK as an adjuvant immunochemotherapy. [10, 11] An adjuvant therapy seeks to keep the cancer from coming back post-treatment, and an immunotherapy targets the immune system. PSK’s effectiveness is thought to stem from its ability to invoke immunomodulation and potentiation of the process by which our immune cells identify and eradicate pre-malignant or malignant cells. [12] PSK from turkey tail mushrooms are regularly used for cancer treatment in Japan. [13]</p>
<p>Beta-glucans in shiitake mushrooms are known to interact with receptors on several types of immune cells. The mushrooms offer anti-tumor properties, not because they directly engage the tumor, but because they activate immune responses in the host. [14] The polysaccharide lentinan, for example, acts as a host defense potentiators which help hosts defend against various types of cancer.</p>
<p>These are just a few examples of the polysaccharides and triterpenes within several mushroom species that have demonstrated anticancer activity. As we rekindle our relationship with nature, it’s important to understand how medicinal fungi like mushrooms can convalesce our well-being. Mushrooms like reishi have been with us for antiquity, and as we evolve into the future, the power of these ancient species are being validated with science.</p>
<p><b>References</b></p>
<p>[1] Unschuld, Paul U. Medicine in China: A History of Pharmaceutics. Berkeley: Univ. of California Pr. 1986</p>
<p>[2] Cör D, Knez Ž, Knez Hrnčič M. Antitumour, antimicrobial, antioxidant and  antiacetylcholinesterase effect of Ganoderma lucidum terpenoids and polysaccharides: A review. Molecules. 2018;23(3):649</p>
<p>[3] Paterson R.R.M. Ganoderma—A therapeutic fungal biofactory. Phytochemistry. 2006;68:1985–2001</p>
<p>[4] Sohretoglu D, Huang S. Ganoderma lucidum polysaccharides as an anti-cancer agent. Anticancer  Agents Med Chem. 2018;18(5):667-674</p>
<p>[5] Liu DL, Li YJ, Yang DH, et al. Ganoderma lucidum derived ganoderenic acid B reverses ABCB1-  mediated multidrug resistance in HepG2/ADM cells. Int J Oncol. 2015;46(5):2029-2038</p>
<p>[6] Masuda Y, Nakayama Y, Tanaka A, Naito K, Konishi M. Antitumor activity of orally administered  maitake α-glucan by stimulating antitumor immune response in murine tumor. PLoS One.  2017;12(3):e0173621</p>
<p>[7] Masuda Y, Ito K, Konishi M, Nanba H. A polysaccharide extracted from Grifola frondosa enhances  the anti-tumor activity of bone marrow-derived dendritic cell-based immunotherapy against murine  colon cancer. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2010;59(10):1531-1541</p>
<p>[8] Chung MJ, Chung CK, Jeong Y, Ham SS. Anticancer activity of subfractions containing pure  compounds of Chaga mushroom (Inonotus obliquus) extract in human cancer cells and in Balbc/c  mice bearing Sarcoma-180 cells. Nutr Res Pract. 2010;4(3):177-182</p>
<p>[9] Lee SH, Hwang HS, Yun JW. Antitumor activity of water extract of a mushroom, Inonotus  obliquus, against HT-29 human colon cancer cells. Phytother Res. 2009;23(12):1784-1789</p>
<p>[10] Lu H, Yang Y, Gad E, et al. TLR2 agonist PSK activates human NK cells and enhances the antitumor  effect of HER2-targeted monoclonal antibody therapy. Clin Cancer Res. 2011;17(21):6742-6753</p>
<p>[11] Sakamoto J, Morita S, Oba K, et al. Efficacy of adjuvant immunochemotherapy with polysaccharide  K for patients with curatively resected colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of centrally randomized  controlled clinical trials. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2006;55(4):404-411</p>
<p>[12] Fritz H, Kennedy DA, Ishii M, et al. Polysaccharide K and Coriolus versicolor extracts for lung cancer:  a systematic review. Integr Cancer Ther. 2015;14(3):201-211</p>
<p>[13] National Cancer Institute. Medicinal Mushrooms (PDQ®)–Health Professional Version.  www.cancer.gov; accessed February 24, 2021</p>
<p>[14] Wasser S. Shiitake (Lentinus edodes). In Coates P, Blackman MR, Betz J, Cragg GM, Levine M, Moss  J, &amp; White JD. Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2010</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/mood-altering-mushrooms</id>
    <published>2021-03-22T14:48:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-03-22T14:49:41-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/mood-altering-mushrooms"/>
    <title>Mood-Altering Mushrooms</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><b>By:</b> <b>Dr.</b> <b>Jason S. </b><b>Lupoi</b><b>, Ph.D.</b></p>
<p>Mental health conditions are a significant detriment to modern society. Approximately, 284 million people suffer from anxiety, and another 264 million people globally [1] have been diagnosed with depression. While there are many pharmaceutical drugs prescribed to help alleviate suffering caused by these mental health conditions, there are natural options that can provide relief as well. For those living (or maybe just existing) with anxiety or depression symptoms, anything that helps improve one’s mental state can make a  significant impact to their quality of life.</p>
<p>Medicinal mushrooms contain molecules that have demonstrated anti-anxiety properties and the ability to lessen depressive symptoms. In one study, a reishi mushroom extract showed similar anti-anxiety properties as the pharmaceutical drug diazepam. [2] Reishi powder also diminished fatigue, anxiety, depression, and provided a better quality of life in 48 breast cancer survivors. [3] The patients were given 1,000 mg of reishi powder three times a day for four weeks. The researchers postulated that “[o]ne explanation for the improvement in depression is that with less fatigue and more energy, these breast cancer survivors were able to do some activities that they previously had given up. These activities brought pleasure into their lives.”</p>
<p>Lion’s mane mushrooms and their beta- and alpha-glucan polysaccharides have also been shown to reduce anxiety and depression symptoms. [4] The four-week study included 30 females aged 35 to 47 years old, who had various ailments, but no specific diseases. They consumed four lion’s mane cookies containing 0.5 g of powdered lion’s mane fruiting bodies or placebo cookies. The study sought to understand the lion’s mane cookies’ clinical effects on menopause, including sleep quality and depression. After evaluating the participants, the researchers found that the group receiving lion’s mane cookies showed decreased depression and anxiety like symptoms. The researchers attributed these effects to the mushroom’s stimulation of nerve growth factor.</p>
<p>Cordyceps mushrooms have also demonstrated antidepressant properties. [5,6] One study used cordyceps mushrooms in conjunction with duloxetine, a common antidepressant (e.g., Cymbalta®). [6] Depression is reported to be 18% higher in people with diabetes compared to the rest of the world’s population. Even more significant is that research has highlighted that depressed diabetics are less likely to stick to an antidiabetic regimen, causing further long-term damage to their well-being. To analyze this, a 2009 study was conducted that suggested that vanadium-enriched cordyceps might be efficacious for diabetes-induced depression. [7] Vanadium salts can mimic insulin, thereby providing a therapeutic benefit. However, trace elements like vanadium can also be toxic in our bodies. In addition to cordyceps’ mood-enhancing properties, they have the added benefit of taking up these trace elements in our bodies, reducing toxicity while preserving the desired clinical effects.</p>
<p>These researchers tested their hypothesis in a follow-up study using rats. [8] They employed tests like evaluating how much the rats swam or climbed objects, which are accepted animal models for depression. The vanadium-enriched mushroom treatment resulted in increased mobility via swimming and climbing, revealing the potential of this two-pronged approach to diabetes-induced depression.</p>
<p>Reishi, lion’s mane, and cordyceps mushrooms provide the fungal power behind several Spore Life Sciences formulations such as Chill Out, containing reishi mushrooms and other medicinal plants such as chamomile and lemon balm which also provide anxiolytic, calming properties; or Focus Performance which includes lion’s mane and cordyceps mushrooms, as well as ashwagandha and gingko biloba. A well-thought-out wellness plan can easily include everyday great all-natural ingredients like functional mushrooms, and with the added validation from the scientific literature, it just makes natural sense.</p>
<p> <strong>References</strong></p>
<p>[1] Sison, G. Depression Statistics 2021 . Global Health Metrics Volume 392, Issue 10159, P178901858</p>
<p>[2] Ali N, Muhammad A, &amp; Akbar S.A. Anxiolytic-like activity of ethanol extract of <i>Ganoderma lucidum</i> (Reishi) in mice. <i>International Journal of Medical Research and Health Sciences</i>. 2016;5:57-60</p>
<p>[3] Zhao H, Zhang Q, Zhao L, Huang X, Wang J, Kang X. Spore powder of <i>Ganoderma lucidum</i> improves cancer-related fatigue in breast cancer patients undergoing endocrine therapy: A Pilot Clinical Trial. <i>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</i>. 2012;2012:809614</p>
<p>[4] Nagano M, Shimizu K, Kondo R, et al. Reduction of depression and anxiety by 4 weeks <i>Hericium</i> <i>erinaceus</i> intake. <i>Biomed Res</i>. 2010;31(4):231-237</p>
<p>[5] Nishizawa K, Torii K, Kawasaki A, et al. Antidepressant-like effect of <i>Cordyceps sinensis</i> in the mouse tail suspension test. <i>Biol Pharm Bull</i>. 2007;30(9):1758-1762</p>
<p>[6] Chen X, Zhang X, Wang C, Feng L, &amp; Wang G. <i>Cordyceps sinensis</i> combined with duloxetine improves sleep symptoms in patients with depression: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. <i>Asia Pacific Journal of Clinical Trials: Nervous System Diseases</i>. 2018;3:136-145</p>
<p>[7] Guo JY, Han CC, Liu YM. A contemporary treatment approach to both diabetes and depression by <i>Cordyceps sinensis</i>, rich in vanadium. <i>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</i>. 2010;7(3):387-389</p>
<p>[8] Guo J, Li C, Wang J, Liu Y, Zhang J. Vanadium-enriched <i>Cordyceps sinensis</i>, a contemporary treatment approach to both diabetes and depression in rats. <i>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</i>. 2011;2011:450316</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/inside-the-fungi-polysaccharides-and-terpenoids</id>
    <published>2021-03-15T13:23:03-04:00</published>
    <updated>2021-03-15T13:23:03-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/inside-the-fungi-polysaccharides-and-terpenoids"/>
    <title>Inside the Fungi: Polysaccharides and Terpenoids</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><b>By:</b> <b>Dr.</b> <b>Jason</b> <b>S.</b> <b>Lupoi</b><b>,</b> <b>Ph.D.</b></p>
<p><b></b>With the growing emphasis on overall health and wellness, millions of individuals have begun to educate themselves on how various plants and fungi lessen their dependence on pharmaceutical drugs.</p>
<p>Fortunately, there are many great natural options readily available to consumers within our reach.</p>
<p>Through a simple search, one can learn about the cannabinoids and terpenes contained in the trichomes of <i>Cannabis sativa</i>; flavonoids like anthocyanins that give many plants like elderberry or pomegranate wonderfully rich and deep shades of purple and red; or the plentiful polysaccharides and various terpenes (e.g., diterpenes, triterpenes) in medicinal mushrooms like maitake, chaga, and turkey tail.</p>
<p>These molecules in turn produce medicinal properties that we look to benefit from, which include antioxidative, anticancer, antiviral, mental health and antianxiety supportive properties – all of which, are increasingly important for dealing with the stressors derived from contemporary society.</p>
<p>The silver lining during crazy and uncertain times like today is that it has driven many individuals to research and learn the best way to use and take advantage of specific plants and fungi that hold powerful medicinal promise. And for every medicinal plant, there are specific, often unique collections of chemicals that convey the therapeutic properties as well. Just as one example, but medicinal or functional mushrooms offer polysaccharides and terpenes.</p>
<p><b>Polysaccharides</b></p>
<p>A polysaccharide is a carbohydrate consisting of a chain of sugar molecules linked together. Cellulose, for example, is like a chain-linked fence of glucose molecules, and this type of polysaccharide is known as a glucan. An α-glucan (alpha-glucan) from maitake mushrooms, called YM-2A has been evaluated for anticancer properties. This polysaccharide stimulates production of cells that enhance our immune systems like tumor necrosis factor α, different interleukins, and through macrophage cell activation. [1] β-glucans (beta-glucans) in shiitake mushrooms are known to interact with receptors on several types of immune cells. The mushrooms offer anti-tumor properties, not because they directly engage the tumor, but because they activate immune responses in the host. [2] The polysaccharide lentinan, for example, acts as a host defense potentiator which helps hosts defend against various types of cancer. Lentinan also confers antiviral, antiparasitic, and antibacterial properties. Shiitake also contains the polysaccharide named KS-2 which has also demonstrated anticancer properties.</p>
<p>Another polysaccharide called krestin, or PSK in turkey tail mushrooms possesses powerful anticancer properties, with one study reporting increased survival in colon cancer patients who received PSK as an adjuvant immunochemotherapy. [3] An adjuvant therapy looks to prevent cancer from coming back post-treatment, and an immunotherapy specifically targets the immune system. PSK also activated natural killer cells and potentiated the chemotherapy drug trastuzumab. [4]</p>
<p>Polysaccharides like PEPS30, PEPS60, and especially PEPS80 in king trumpet mushrooms, provide strong antioxidants that hunt free radicals and promote key antioxidant enzymes like superoxide dismutase that help reduce oxidative stress. [5] King trumpet mushrooms also contain polysaccharides, offering anticancer properties through their ability to induce changes within our immune systems. Two such polysaccharides, named PEP-1, and PEP-2, showed their ability to provoke apoptosis, or cell death. [6] Like other mushrooms that display anticancer properties, king trumpet polysaccharides act on the host organism’s immune system, improving its ability to fend off the invaders, in part, by stimulating the response of natural killer cells, helping them be better at their respective immune functions. [7] One such water-soluble polysaccharide named PEPw has shown to inhibit renal cancer tumor growth.</p>
<p>Additionally, high-molecular weight polysaccharides from <i>Antrodia</i> <i>cinnamomea</i> have demonstrated adjuvant effects on dendritic cells and in immunotherapy vaccines for cancer. [8] The polysaccharide galactomannan provides an example of an immunostimulatory compound extracted from <i>Antrodia</i> that enhances resistances against bacterial attacks in the early stages of an infection, but also lessens the risk of severe infection by lessening the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines. [9]</p>
<p><b>Triterpenes</b></p>
<p>Terpenes are characterized as molecules that give plants and fungi their flavors and aromas. Mushrooms contain assorted monoterpenes, sesquiterpenes, diterpenes, and triterpenes. Monoterpenes contain two linked isoprene (C5H8) units whereas sesquiterpenes contain three linked isoprenes. A di- or triterpene consists of even more isoprene units. Diterpenes, for example, contain four linked isoprene units, whereas triterpenes contain six isoprene units. (Note: a terpene contains only hydrogen and carbon atoms; a terpenoid has other atoms like oxygen.)</p>
<p>Chaga mushrooms contain multiple triterpenoids such as the unglamorously named 3β-hydroxy-lanosta-8,24-dien-21-al, inotodiol, and lanosterol, and each of these molecules showed effectiveness against lung, stomach, breast, and cervical cancer cell lines with low toxicity to normal cells. [10] Extracts of the chaga mushrooms were further refined until three subfractions were obtained. Each subfraction conferred antitumor activity.</p>
<p>The triterpenoid methyl antcinate K isolated from <i>A. </i><i>cinnamomea</i> promoted dendritic cells, which are vital leukocytes or white blood cells. [11] Dendritic cells essentially assist T-cells by processing antigens (foreign substances or toxins) and presenting them to the T-cells, which “are like soldiers who search out and destroy the targeted invaders.”</p>
<p>While the points I mentioned above are comprehensive, they reflect only a fraction of the potential medicinal benefits mushrooms can offer one's health and wellness. Spore is excited to be leading the charge with its intelligent functional mushroom formulations, which have been thoughtfully blended to highlight the natural power of these mushrooms and enhanced with other highly effective all-natural ingredients. This is evident in formulations such as Protect+Defend, designed to boost one’s immune’s system, or Mike’s Mushroom Mix, which is a powerful anti-inflammatory.</p>
<p><strong>References</strong></p>
<p>[1] Masuda Y, Nakayama Y, Tanaka A, Naito K, Konishi M. Antitumor activity of orally administered maitake α-glucan by stimulating antitumor immune response  in murine tumor. PLoS One. 2017;12(3):e0173621</p>
<p>[2] Wasser S. Shiitake (Lentinus edodes).In Coates P, Blackman MR, Betz J, Cragg GM, Levine M, Moss J, &amp;  White JD. Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements. 2010</p>
<p>[3] Sakamoto J, Morita S, Oba K, et al. Efficacy of adjuvant immunochemotherapy with polysaccharide K  for patients with curatively resected colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of centrally randomized  controlled clinical trials. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2006;55(4):404-411</p>
<p>[4] Lu H, Yang Y, Gad E, et al. TLR2 agonist PSK activates human NK cells and enhances the antitumor effect of HER2-targeted monoclonal antibody therapy. Clin Cancer Res.  2011;17(21):6742-6753</p>
<p>[5] Zhang B, Li Y, Zhang F, Linhardt RJ, Zeng G, Zhang A. Extraction, structure, and bioactivities of the  polysaccharides from Pleurotus eryngii: A review. Int J Biol Macromol. 2020;150:1342-1347</p>
<p>[6] Ren D, Wang N, Guo J, Yuan L, Yang X. Chemical characterization of Pleurotus eryngii polysaccharide  and its tumor-inhibitory effects against human hepatoblastoma HepG-2 cells. Carbohydr Polym. 2016;138:123-133</p>
<p>[7] Yang Z, Xu J, Fu Q, et al. Antitumor activity of a polysaccharide from Pleurotus eryngii on mice bearing  renal cancer. Carbohydr Polym. 2013;95(2):615-620</p>
<p>[8] Lin CC, Pan IH, Li YR, et al. The adjuvant effects of high-molecule-weight polysaccharides purified from  Antrodia cinnamomea on dendritic cell function and DNA vaccines. PLoS One. 2015;10(2):e0116191</p>
<p>[9] Perera N, Yang FL, Lu YT, Li LH, Hua KF, Wu SH. Antrodia cinnamomea galactomannan elicits immuno-stimulatory activity through toll-like receptor 4. Int J Biol Sci. 2018;14(10):1378-1388</p>
<p>[10] Chung MJ, Chung CK, Jeong Y, Ham SS. Anticancer activity of subfractions containing pure  compounds of Chaga mushroom (Inonotus obliquus) extract in human cancer cells and in Balbc/c  mice bearing Sarcoma-180 cells. Nutr Res Pract. 2010;4(3):177-182</p>
<p>[11] Yu YL, Chen IH, Shen KY, et al. A triterpenoid methyl antcinate K isolated from Antrodia cinnamomea  promotes dendritic cell activation and Th2 differentiation. Eur J Immunol. 2009;39(9):2482-2491</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/is-there-an-entourage-effect-in-medicinal-mushrooms</id>
    <published>2021-03-09T18:07:48-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-03-09T18:07:48-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/is-there-an-entourage-effect-in-medicinal-mushrooms"/>
    <title>Is There an Entourage Effect in Medicinal Mushrooms?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><b>By:</b> <b>Dr.</b> <b>Michele Ross, </b><b>Ph.D.</b></p>
<p>Medicinal mushrooms have a wide range of benefits, from fighting inflammation, to boosting cognitive function, to supporting the immune system, and increasing energy. But how do these magic mushrooms do it? While all mushrooms are beneficial for immune system support, each functional mushroom has its own strengths when it comes to specific health benefits. Some mushrooms are better for energy, some are better for focus, and some are better for relaxation. Is there an entourage effect happening in mushrooms like there is in other plant. Medicines?</p>
<p><b>What is the Entourage Effect? </b>     </p>
<p>The Entourage Effect, first posed by Dr. Raphael Mechoulam and Dr. Shimon Ben-Shabat in 1998 and expanded on by Dr. Ethan Russo, suggests that compounds in the cannabis plant such as cannabinoids, terpenes, and flavonoids work synergistically to deliver more medicinal benefits together than the sum of each of the isolated compounds.[1,2] It is believed many botanical medicines, including magic mushrooms and kratom, also have an entourage effect, whereby their numerous components work better together than an isolated extract of any active ingredient. This means taking a full-spectrum extract of mushroom may be more effective for some wellness needs than taking extracts of its single active ingredients, for example.</p>
<p>We know that different strains of functional and psychedelic mushrooms contain different amounts of active chemicals, just like different strains of cannabis or other botanical medicines including kratom and ayahuasca. Medicinal mushrooms are made of four major classes of active compounds: polysaccharides, polypeptides, alkaloids, and triterpenes.[3] Let’s explore what they do.</p>
<p><b>What are Polysaccharides in Functional </b><b>M</b><b>ushrooms?</b></p>
<p>While polysaccharides exist in bacteria, yeast, plants, and fungi, the specific type that are in mushrooms are called alpha-glucans and beta-glucans. Alpha-glucans are starches that can help regulate blood sugar and are helpful in the prevention of diabetes.[4] However, when it comes to medicinal benefits, beta-glucans are much more powerful than alpha-glucans. It’s important to make sure your mushrooms supplement is high in beta-glucans as opposed to alpha-glucans, as different methods of growing mushrooms can alter their content.</p>
<p>Certain mushrooms naturally contain high amounts of beta-glucans compared to other functional mushrooms. These include reishi mushroom, turkey tail mushroom, and maitake mushroom. While there are hundreds of beta-glucans, some of the most well researched ones include lentinan, schizophyllan, ganoderan, grifolan, and polysaccharide-krestin (PSK). Ganoderan, for example, is found in reishi mushrooms and works as an antioxidant and an anti-inflammatory, promoting heart health.[5] PSK is found in turkey tail mushrooms and is powerful at killing cancer cells.[6]</p>
<p><b>Polypeptides</b></p>
<p>Polypeptides are the building blocks of proteins, and found in many of the foods we eat, including mushrooms. Each of these polypeptides can have health benefits. Lentinus squarrosulus, for example, is an wild edible mushroom that contains polypeptides that have anticancer properties.[7] There are likely many more medicinal polypeptides in mushrooms that we will identify after more research into these amazing fungi.</p>
<p><b> What are Terpenoids in Medicinal Mushrooms?</b></p>
<p>Terpenoids are the largest class of chemicals extracted from plants, as over 20,000 terpenoids have been identified. The term terpenoid is often used interchangeably with the word terpene, but in fact, these are two different compounds. Many people are familiar with terpenes, the chemicals that give cannabis and essential oils their smell, flavor, and health benefits. They are also found in other plants, such as mushrooms. When the chemicals are in the live plant, they are terpenes. When they have been exposed to oxygen, which happens in the process of drying plants for consumption, these terpenes are oxidized into terpenoids.</p>
<p>Medicinal mushrooms contain over 275 terpenoids and are further divided into classes with a least five monoterpenes, 70 sesquiterpenes, 44 diterpenes and 166 triterpenes discovered. [8] The difference between the triterpenes, diterpenes, sesquiterpenes, and monoterpenes is the number of carbon units in their chemical structures. Each of the terpenoids in mushrooms has significant medicinal benefits, and each mushroom variety has their own combination of terpenoids. Some anticancer and neuroprotective triterpenoids found in reishi mushroom include gandoderic acid and its derivatives.</p>
<p><b>What are Alkaloids in Functional </b><b>M</b><b>ushrooms?</b></p>
<p>Alkaloids are one of the most the active ingredients in mushrooms, responsible for hallucinogenic effects and neuroprotection in some species. Scientifically, the term alkaloid refers to organic compounds containing at least one nitrogen atom and are usually basic as opposed to acidic. Plants, animals, bacteria, and fungi can all produce alkaloids, and most have pharmacological activities in the human body. Plant-based alkaloids include caffeine, cocaine, morphine, and nicotine, while the two major fungi alkaloids, found in species of psychedelic “magic mushrooms” are psilocybin and psilocin.</p>
<p>Not all mushroom alkaloids cause hallucinations or get you high. For example, cordycepin is an alkaloid found in cordyceps mushroom that has many potential benefits, including killing leukemia cells, acting as an antidepressant, and enhancing cellular energy.[9]</p>
<p><b>Taking Multiple </b><b>M</b><b>ushrooms </b><b>T</b><b>ogether may be More Effective Than </b><b>T</b><b>aking </b><b>J</b><b>ust </b><b>O</b><b>ne</b></p>
<p>Functional mushrooms contain many health-promoting chemical compounds, but no single mushroom contains them all. By combining mushrooms, you’ll have exposure to even more active ingredients and be able to increase the entourage effect of medicinal mushrooms. Many of our formulas have more than one mushroom, and our favorite formula, Mike’s Mushroom Mix, contains a mix of ten functional mushrooms. So, if you’re looking to experience the entourage effect in mushrooms, Mike’s Mushroom Mix is your best bet, with agarikon, antrodia, chaga, cordyceps, king trumpets, lion’s mane, maitake, reishi, shiitake, and turkey tail mushrooms.</p>
<p><b>What About </b><b>C</b><b>ombining </b><b>M</b><b>edicinal </b><b>M</b><b>ushrooms </b><b>W</b><b>ith </b><b>O</b><b>ther </b><b>P</b><b>lants?</b></p>
<p>Medicinal mushrooms pair really well with adaptogens, which are herbs that lower stress hormones. You’ll find Ayurvedic herb ashwagandha in our Chill Out formula paired with reishi mushroom, and panax ginseng paired with cordyceps mushrooms in our Energy Performance formula. Certain chemicals in reishi mushrooms like genistein and kaempferol boost the endocannabinoid system, so taking reishi, found in many of our formulas, pairs well with using CBD and other hemp products. </p>
<p><b> </b></p>
<p><b>References:</b></p>
<p>[1] Ben-Shabat S, Fride E, Sheskin T, Tamiri T, Rhee MH, Vogel Z, Bisogno T, De Petrocellis L, Di Marzo V, Mechoulam R. An entourage effect: inactive endogenous fatty acid glycerol esters enhance 2-arachidonoyl-glycerol cannabinoid activity. Eur J Pharmacol. 1998 Jul 17;353(1):23-31.</p>
<p>[2] Russo EB. Taming THC: potential cannabis synergy and phytocannabinoid-terpenoid entourage effects. <i>Br J </i><i>Pharmacol</i>. 2011;163(7):1344-1364</p>
<p>[3] Phan CW., Tan E.YY., Sabaratnam V. (2018) Bioactive Molecules in Edible and Medicinal Mushrooms for Human Wellness. In: Mérillon JM., Ramawat K. (eds) Bioactive Molecules in Food. Reference Series in Phytochemistry. Springer, Cham</p>
<p>[4]Hong L, Xun M, Wutong W. Anti-diabetic effect of an alpha-glucan from fruit body of maitake (<i>Grifola</i> <i>frondosa</i>) on KKAy mice. <i>J Pharm </i><i>Pharmacol</i><i>. </i>2007;59:575–582</p>
<p>[5]Feng ZL, Fang TJ, Qian YX, Rong WH (2014) The clinical research for Ganoderan’s effect on preventing and treating cerebral arteriosclerosis through inhibiting NADPH oxidizing enzyme expression. Pak J Pharm Sci 27:1107–1111</p>
<p>[6] PDQ Integrative, Alternative, and Complementary Therapies Editorial Board. Medicinal Mushrooms (PDQ®): Patient Version. 2020 Apr 21. In: PDQ Cancer Information Summaries [Internet]. Bethesda (MD): National Cancer Institute (US); 2002-. Available from: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK424937/</p>
<p>[7] Prateep A, Sumkhemthong S, Suksomtip M, Chanvorachote P, Chaotham C. Peptides extracted from edible mushroom: Lentinus squarrosulus induces apoptosis in human lung cancer cells. Pharm Biol. 2017 Dec;55(1):1792-1799</p>
<p>[8] Dasgupta A, Acharya K. Mushrooms: an emerging resource for therapeutic terpenoids. 3 Biotech. 2019 Oct;9(10):369</p>
<p>[9] Tuli HS, Sandhu SS, Sharma AK. Pharmacological and therapeutic potential of Cordyceps with special reference to Cordycepin. <i>3 Biotech</i>. 2014;4(1):1-12</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/the-natural-power-behind-energy-performance</id>
    <published>2021-02-05T12:44:59-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-02-06T12:06:56-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/the-natural-power-behind-energy-performance"/>
    <title>The Natural Power Behind Energy Performance</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>What Is It?</strong><br>This energy blend combines the power of functional mushrooms with natural energy enhancers to keep you running at peak performance – even on your toughest days.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>What’s In It?</strong><br>This potent formula is centered around the Cordyceps mushroom, and Maitake mushrooms, enhanced with a potent mix of all-natural energy boosting ingredients. </p>
<ul>
<li>
<em>Cordyceps - </em>for their natural energy properties and metabolism boosting functionality and help with oxygen intake for better endurance</li>
<li>
<em>Maitake - </em>for metabolism support and immune-boosting power</li>
<li>
<em>Guarana </em>- for natural energy production</li>
<li>
<em>Green tea extract </em>- increase metabolic function</li>
<li>
<em>Panax ginseng </em>- reduce fatigue</li>
<li>
<em>Turmeric root </em>- helps with inflammation</li>
</ul>
<p> <br><strong>What Does It Do?</strong><br>Energy Performance with its scientifically proven ability to help the lungs absorb oxygen more efficiently at the cellular level, this potent mushroom will provide you with increased endurance and energy whenever you need it.  Packed with rich profile of phytochemicals such as polysaccharides, triterpenoids, amino acids, and polyphenols, as well as additions of vitamins B, B-12, C, and D and minerals will support your body ability to product natural sustained energy, on top of boosting metabolism support, immune strength and support, anti-aging, and longevity.<br><strong> </strong><br><strong>How Does It Work?</strong><br>The Energy Performance formula provides an intelligent array of fungal molecules demonstrated in the scientific literature to offer wellness properties.</p>
<p>Traditional uses of <strong>cordyceps mushrooms</strong> include promotion of health, longevity, and athletic power and endurance. [1] In 1993, Chinese runners who had ingested cordyceps achieved records in several running events, thrusting these mushrooms on the world stage as potential energy enhancers. Thus, cordyceps is used in Spore products to provide a burst of energy. One study demonstrated that, with or without exercising, cordyceps improved exercise endurance by activating skeletal muscle metabolic regulators and increasing antioxidants. [1] A double-blind, placebo-controlled trial also demonstrated these findings in older adults (ages 50-75 years) who ingested 333 mg of dried mushrooms. [2] Aerobic performance improved and the ingestion of the mushrooms pointed to resistance to fatigue. </p>
<p>Glucans from <em>Grifola frondosa</em> or <strong>maitake mushrooms</strong> provide strong antioxidant and immune-supporting properties [3-5], providing evidence for anti-aging capabilities. Antioxidative properties worked by augmenting key enzymes like superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase activity, which in turn, catalyze the destruction of the superoxide radical and reduce lipid hydroperoxides to alcohols and hydrogen peroxide to water, respectively. Additionally, these glucans increased interleukine-2 (IL-2) production, an immunocytokine that has strong immune-enhancing properties providing the most effective cytokine for T cell biology (a type of white blood cell), as well as the ability to boost the activity of natural killer cells, another type of lymphocyte vital to our immune systems. Malondialdehyde (a common marker for oxidative stress) content in the liver was reduced, further demonstrating maitake’s antioxidant properties. [4] What’s more, α-glucan from maitake offers anti-tumor activity by promoting the production of cells that enhance our immune systems like tumor necrosis factor α, different interleukins, and through macrophage cell activation. [6] And a human clinical trial showed that maitake mushrooms led to increased antibodies in in response to influenza type A virus H1N1 after study participants took 20 maitake tablets per day. [7] Maitake mushrooms also help improve metabolism, showing increased fat metabolism [8,9] and other age-related metabolic issues such as glucose/insulin metabolism (e.g., hyperglycemia) [10].<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Guarana </strong>seeds contain more caffeine than any other plant including approximately four times as much as coffee. [11,12] Thus, guarana provides a source of natural energy exemplified by the surge in energy drinks containing it. The stimulating effects of guarana are longer lasting than caffeine.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Green Tea Extract </strong>provides a panoply of various molecules that are beneficent for our health, such as antioxidants and polyphenols like the catechins which include epicatechin, epigallocatechin, epicatechingallate, and epigallocatechin gallate, or EGCG. In addition to antioxidant and anti-cancer properties [13], green tea extract is beneficial for metabolism, specifically lipid metabolism in overweight people [14]. A meta-analysis concluded that drinking green tea can reduce total cholesterol and low-density lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL). EGCG helps prevent an enzyme from breaking down norepinephrine, a hormone, leading to an increase in the hormone’s concentration. [15,16] This results in the breaking down of fat, and the caffeine and EGCG in green tea may potentiate the effect. [17]<br><strong><em></em></strong></p>
<p><strong><em>Panax ginseng</em></strong><strong> (ginseng)</strong> is a well-known natural stimulant for energy and vitality. A steroid within ginseng called dammarane steroid has demonstrated anti-inflammatory effects on skeletal muscle after muscle-damaging exercise. [18] The dominant molecule within a ginseng extract, called ginsenoside Ro, is also thought to combat inflammation and boost skeletal muscle performance. [19] The mechanism of ginseng’s ability to help prevent fatigue, especially following exercise, is thought to reside in its decreasing plasma lactate, ammonia, and creatine kinase, while increasing serum glucose levels. Other studies have reported ginseng’s ability to decrease oxidative stress in skeletal muscle. [20]</p>
<p>Long used in the culinary industry to provide color to dishes,<strong> turmeric root </strong>has become much more of a household spice in recent times due to the medicinal properties it bestows. For example, turmeric and its phytochemicals such as curcumin are known anti-inflammatory agents as has been demonstrated in pre-clinical and clinical investigations. [21-23] Because of its anti-inflammatory properties, turmeric and curcumin have been studied as a treatment option for diseases where inflammation plays a strong role, such as Alzheimer’s disease, cancer, and arthritis. [22] As an example, curcumin provided relief in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. [23]<br> <br>These statements have not been evaluated by the Food &amp; Drug Administration. This product is not intended to diagnose, treat, cure, or prevent any disease.<br><strong> </strong><br><strong>References</strong><br>[1] Kumar R, Negi PS, Singh B, Ilavazhagan G, Bhargava K, Sethy NK. Cordyceps sinensis promotes exercise endurance capacity of rats by activating skeletal muscle metabolic regulators. J Ethnopharmacol. 2011;136(1):260-266.<br>[2] Chen S, Li Z, Krochmal R, Abrazado M, Kim W, Cooper CB. Effect of Cs-4 (Cordyceps sinensis) on exercise performance in healthy older subjects: a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. J Altern Complement Med. 2010;16(5):585-590.<br>[3] Vetvicka V, Vetvickova J. Immune-enhancing effects of Maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) and Shiitake (<em>Lentinula edodes</em>) extracts. <em>Ann Transl Med</em>. 2014;2(2):14.<br>[4] Hong L, Weiyub W, Qina W, Shuzhena G, and Lebin W. Antioxidant and immunomodulatory effects of a a-glucan from fruit body of maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>). <em>Food and Agricultural Immunology</em>. 2013;24(4):409-418.<br>[5] Yeh JY, Hsieh LH, Wu KT, Tsai CF. Antioxidant properties and antioxidant compounds of various extracts from the edible basidiomycete <em>Grifola frondosa</em> (Maitake). <em>Molecules</em>. 2011;16(4):3197-3211.<br>[6] Masuda Y, Nakayama Y, Tanaka A, Naito K, Konishi M. Antitumor activity of orally administered maitake α-glucan by stimulating antitumor immune response in murine tumor. <em>PLoS One</em>. 2017;12(3):e0173621.<br>[7] Nishihira J, Sato M, Tanaka A, Okamatsu M, Azuma T. et al. Maitake mushrooms (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) enhances antibody production in response to influenza vaccination in healthy adult volunteers concurrent with alleviation of common cold symptoms. <em>Functional Foods in Health and Disease</em>. 2017; 7:462-482.<br>[8] Kabir Y, Hoshino T, Komai M, Kimura S. Histopathological changes in spontaneously hypertensive rats after feeding shiitake (<em>Lentinus edodes</em>) and maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) mushroom diets. <em>J Clin Biochem Nutr</em> 1989;6:187-193.<br>[9] Kubo K, Nanba H. The effect of maitake mushrooms on liver and serum lipids. <em>Altern Ther Health Med</em> 1996;2:62-66.<br>[10] Talpur NA, Echard BW, Fan AY, Jaffari O, Bagchi D, Preuss HG. Antihypertensive and metabolic effects of whole Maitake mushroom powder and its fractions in two rat strains. <em>Mol Cell Biochem</em>. 2002;237(1-2):129-136.<br>[11] Beck HT. Caffeine, alcohol, and sweeteners. In: Prance GT (ed). <em>The Cultural History of Plants</em>. New York: Routledge. 2005;173–90.<br>[12] Smith N, Atroch AL. Guaraná's Journey from regional tonic to aphrodisiac and global energy drink. <em>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</em>. 2010;7(3):279-282.<br>[13] Musial C, Kuban-Jankowska A, Gorska-Ponikowska M. Beneficial properties of green tea catechins. <em>Int J Mol Sci</em>. 2020;21(5):1744.<br>[14] Yuan F, Dong H, Fang K, Gong J, Lu F. Effects of green tea on lipid metabolism in overweight or obese people: A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. <em>Mol Nutr Food Res</em>. 2018;62(1):10.1002/mnfr.201601122.<br>[15] Lu H, Meng X, Yang CS. Enzymology of methylation of tea catechins and inhibition of catechol-O-methyltransferase by (-)-epigallocatechin gallate. <em>Drug Metab Dispos</em>. 2003;31(5):572-579.<br>[16] Westerterp-Plantenga MS. Green tea catechins, caffeine and body-weight regulation. <em>Physiol Behav</em>. 2010;100(1):42-46.<br>[17] Dulloo AG, Seydoux J, Girardier L, Chantre P, Vandermander J. Green tea and thermogenesis: interactions between catechin-polyphenols, caffeine and sympathetic activity. <em>Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord</em>. 2000;24(2):252-258.<br>[18] Yu SH, Huang CY, Lee SD, et al. Decreased eccentric exercise-induced macrophage infiltration in skeletal muscle after supplementation with a class of ginseng-derived steroids. <em>PLoS One</em>. 2014;9(12):e114649.<br>[19] Ma GD, Chiu CH, Hsu YJ, Hou CW, Chen YM, Huang CC. Changbai Mountain Ginseng (<em>Panax ginseng</em> C.A. Mey) extract supplementation improves exercise performance and energy utilization and decreases fatigue-associated parameters in mice. <em>Molecules</em>. 2017;22(2):237.<br>[20] Zhuang CL, Mao XY, Liu S, et al. Ginsenoside Rb1 improves postoperative fatigue syndrome by reducing skeletal muscle oxidative stress through activation of the PI3K/Akt/Nrf2 pathway in aged rats. <em>Eur J Pharmacol</em>. 2014;740:480-487.<br>[21] Chattopadhyay I, Biswas K, Bandyopadhyay U, Banerjee R. Turmeric and curcumin: Biological actions and medicinal applications. Current Science. 2004;87:44-53.<br>[22] Ghosh S, Banerjee S, Sil PC. The beneficial role of curcumin on inflammation, diabetes and neurodegenerative disease: A recent update. <em>Food Chem Toxicol</em>. 2015;83:111-124.<br>[23] Deodhar SD, Sethi R, Srimal RC. Preliminary study on antirheumatic activity of curcumin (diferuloyl methane). <em>Indian J Med Res</em>. 1980;71:632-634.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-the-protect-defend-works-to-help-boost-your-immune-system</id>
    <published>2021-02-05T12:43:19-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-02-05T12:43:19-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-the-protect-defend-works-to-help-boost-your-immune-system"/>
    <title>How the Protect+Defend Works to Help Boost Your Immune System</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<strong>What Is It?</strong><br>This adaptogenic blend contains a plethora of antioxidants, vitamins, and minerals to supercharge your immune system, boost your metabolism, and improve your gut health every day.<br> <br><strong>What’s In It?</strong><br>This formula contains a mix of different mushrooms designed for supercharged immune function and longevity including:
<ul>
<li>
<em>Turkey tail - </em>for its immune boosting, anti-cancer, and gut health properties,</li>
<li>
<em>Chaga - </em>to support overall health,</li>
<li>
<em>Reishi </em>- to enhance immune function and flood the body and mind with tranquility</li>
<li>
<em>Maitake - </em>for metabolism support and immune-boosting power.</li>
<li>
<em>Elderberry - </em>for rich nutritional and antioxidants profile</li>
<li>
<em>Vitamin C </em><em>- </em>to boost immunity and risk of chronic disease</li>
<li>
<em>Vitamin D </em><em>- </em>strengthen immune function and fights disease</li>
<li>
<em>Zinc </em><em>- </em>rich in antioxidants </li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What Does It Do?</strong><br>Protect + Defend’s rich profile of phytochemicals such as polysaccharides, triterpenoids, amino acids, and polyphenols, as well as additions of vitamins B, B-12, C, and D and minerals will support your overall health and keep your body’s defense operating at its full capacity. It also helps with metabolism support, immune strength and support, anti-aging, and longevity, and strengthening liver function and gut health.<br> <br><strong>How Does It Work?</strong><br>The Protect + Defend formula provides an intelligent array of fungal molecules demonstrated in the scientific literature to offer wellness properties.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Reishi mushrooms</strong>, for example, called “the mushroom of immortality” [1], have been studied for their immune-enhancing, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-tumor, and antimicrobial properties. [2] <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> – the species relevant to this formula – is reported to have over 400 bioactive compounds mostly comprised of polysaccharides and triterpenoids. The immune-enhancing properties of reishi polysaccharides work by increasing the amounts of key immune cells such as natural killer, B-lymphocyte, T-lymphocyte white blood cells, dendritic cells, phagocytes that protect our bodies from foreign particles and may also be examples of white blood cells. A more robust immune system, in turn, is vital in cancer treatment, and reishi polysaccharides stimulate cancer resistance through their immune-enhancing capabilities, by inducing apoptosis (cell death) of cancerous cells, and through their anti-cancer preventing activity. [3,4] Reishi triterpenes offer anti-cancer properties as well, through their toxicity to cancer cells, anti-metastatic effects, and induction of apoptosis. [3-5] Reishi polysaccharides and triterpenes have shown antioxidant and antimicrobial properties, with the terpenes presenting higher antioxidative capacities. The mushroom’s polysaccharides have also demonstrated anti-aging properties through their ability to protect fibroblasts (cells that provides structural framework in mammalian tissue and aids wound healing) from harmful ultraviolet B (UVB) radiation. [6] The UVB treated cells revealed increased signs of aging and reactive oxygen species and decreased cell viability, but when cells were treated with UVB <em>and</em> reishi polysaccharides, the UVB reactive oxygen species were eliminated. Reishi mushrooms also have been used for their sedative, calming properties. In one study, a reishi extract showed similar anti-anxiety properties as the pharmaceutical drug diazepam. [7] Reishi powder also diminished fatigue, anxiety, and depression, and provided a better quality of life in 48 breast cancer survivors. [8]</p>
<p>Glucans from <em>Grifola frondosa</em> or <strong>maitake mushrooms</strong> provide strong antioxidant and immune-supporting properties [9-11], providing evidence for anti-aging capabilities. Antioxidative properties worked by augmenting key enzymes like superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase activity, which in turn, catalyze the destruction of the superoxide radical and reduce lipid hydroperoxides to alcohols and hydrogen peroxide to water, respectively. Additionally, these glucans increased interleukine-2 (IL-2) production, an immunocytokine that has strong immune-enhancing properties providing the most effective cytokine for T cell biology (a type of white blood cell), as well as the ability to boost the activity of natural killer cells, another type of lymphocyte vital to our immune systems. Malondialdehyde (a common marker for oxidative stress) content in the liver was reduced, further demonstrating maitake’s antioxidant properties. [10] What’s more, α-glucan from maitake offers anti-tumor activity by promoting the production of cells that enhance our immune systems like tumor necrosis factor α, different interleukins, and through macrophage cell activation. [12] And a human clinical trial showed that maitake mushrooms led to increased antibodies in in response to influenza type A virus H1N1 after study participants took 20 maitake tablets per day. [13] Maitake mushrooms also help improve metabolism, showing increased fat metabolism [14,15] and other age-related metabolic issues such as glucose/insulin metabolism (e.g., hyperglycemia) [16].<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Chaga mushrooms </strong>offer anticancer, immune-enhancing, antioxidant, anti-hyperglycemic, and anti-mutagenic (gene-protecting) properties. [17] Chaga contains compounds such as 3β-hydroxy-lanosta-8,24-dien-21-al, inotodiol (a triterpene), and lanosterol and each of these molecules showed effectiveness against multiple cancer cell lines with low toxicity to normal cells. [18] Polysaccharides extracted from chaga have reduced tumor size. [19] Chaga mushrooms also provide immune support, antimutagenic, antimicrobial, and antioxidant activity, and anti-hyperglycemic properties. [17] For example, chaga mushroom dosing led to decreased DNA damage and an improvement in deformed structures in zebrafish exposed to UVB radiation. [20] Chaga antioxidant capability prevented the formation of reactive oxygen species helping lessen oxidative stress induced by UV treatment and reduced the amount of pro-inflammatory cytokines brought about by the radiation. [21] Like reishi mushrooms, chaga aids as an antihyperglycemic agent due to its antioxidative properties and its ability to provide protection against cellular damage. [22] Chaga mushrooms also provide protection against liver injury by eliminating free radicals, inhibiting the leakage of key enzymes from the induced damage, and decreasing malondialdehyde formation. [23]</p>
<p>Like the other mushrooms in Protect + Defend, <strong>turkey tail mushrooms </strong>provide strong antioxidant properties. [24] In addition to polysaccharides and triterpenes, turkey tail offers many phenolic species like flavonols and flavonoids like quercetin. And also like other mushrooms within Protect + Defend, turkey tail mushrooms demonstrate genoprotective capabilities. [25] In addition to its polysaccharides, turkey tail contains polysaccharides that are also bound to proteins in complexes called polysaccharopeptides. Krestin (PSK) and polysaccharide peptide (PSP) are two such molecules that have strong immune-enhancing properties. PSP, for example, has been shown to increase white blood cells [26] and PSK stimulates natural killer immune cells. [27] PSK has also shown powerful anticancer properties, with one study measuring an increased survival in colon cancer patients who received PSK as an adjuvant immunochemotherapy. [28] An adjuvant therapy seeks to keep the cancer from coming back post-treatment, and an immunotherapy targets the immune system. Turkey tail mushrooms also increase gut health since they contain prebiotics. One study found that consuming 3.6 g per day of PSP from turkey tail led to beneficial microbiome changes and reduced the growth of infectious bacteria such as <em>E. coli </em>and <em>Shigella</em>. [29] Another study measured higher concentrations of beneficial gut bacteria such as <em>Bifidobacterium </em>and <em>Lactobacillus </em>while detrimental bacteria like <em>Clostridium</em> and <em>Staphylococcus</em> were lessened. [30]</p>
<p>The use of <strong>elderberry </strong>extract provides a well-known supplement for combating the common cold and influenza and has provided respiratory benefits to air travelers. [31,32]<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Vitamin C </strong>is an antioxidant and supports cellular functions that improve immunity, in part through its supporting in the proliferation of key white blood cells. [33] It also helps treat and prevent respiratory and systemic infections.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Vitamin D3 </strong>helps fight disease such as reducing one’s risk of heart disease [34] and reducing the probability of influenza infection [35]. It also has been implicated as improving the symptoms of depression. [36]<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Zinc citrate </strong>is a dietary supplement that provides antioxidant properties, strengthens the immune system, and promotes healthy aging. [37]<br> <br>These statements have not been evaluated by the Food &amp; Drug Administration. This product is not intended to diagnose, treat, cure, or prevent any disease.<br> <br><strong>References</strong><br>[1] Stamets P. (2000). <em>Growing Gourmet and Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. Berkeley, CA: Ten Speed Press.<br>[2] Sanodiya BS, Thakur GS, Baghel RK, Prasad GB, Bisen PS. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em>: a potent pharmacological macrofungus. <em>Curr Pharm Biotechnol</em>. 2009;10(8):717-742.<br>[3] Cör D, Knez Ž, Knez Hrnčič M. Antitumour, antimicrobial, antioxidant and antiacetylcholinesterase effect of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> terpenoids and polysaccharides: A review. <em>Molecules</em>. 2018;23(3):649.<br>[4] Paterson R.R.M. Ganoderma—A therapeutic fungal biofactory. <em>Phytochemistry</em>. 2006;68:1985–2001.<br>[5] Sohretoglu D, Huang S. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> polysaccharides as an anti-cancer agent. <em>Anticancer Agents Med Chem</em>. 2018;18(5):667-674.<br>[6] Zeng Q, Zhou F, Lei L, et al. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> polysaccharides protect fibroblasts against UVB-induced photoaging. <em>Mol Med Rep</em>. 2017;15(1):111-116.<br>[7] Ali N, Muhammad A, &amp; Akbar S.A. Anxiolytic-like activity of ethanol extract of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> (Reishi) in mice. <em>International Journal of Medical Research and Health Sciences</em>. 2016;5:57-60.<br>[8] Zhao H, Zhang Q, Zhao L, Huang X, Wang J, Kang X. Spore powder of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> improves cancer-related fatigue in breast cancer patients undergoing endocrine therapy: A Pilot Clinical Trial. <em>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</em>. 2012;2012:809614.<br>[9] Vetvicka V, Vetvickova J. Immune-enhancing effects of Maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) and Shiitake (<em>Lentinula edodes</em>) extracts. <em>Ann Transl Med</em>. 2014;2(2):14.<br>[10] Hong L, Weiyub W, Qina W, Shuzhena G, and Lebin W. Antioxidant and immunomodulatory effects of a a-glucan from fruit body of maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>). <em>Food and Agricultural Immunology</em>. 2013;24(4):409-418.<br>[11] Yeh JY, Hsieh LH, Wu KT, Tsai CF. Antioxidant properties and antioxidant compounds of various extracts from the edible basidiomycete <em>Grifola frondosa</em> (Maitake). <em>Molecules</em>. 2011;16(4):3197-3211.<br>[12] Masuda Y, Nakayama Y, Tanaka A, Naito K, Konishi M. Antitumor activity of orally administered maitake α-glucan by stimulating antitumor immune response in murine tumor. <em>PLoS One</em>. 2017;12(3):e0173621.<br>[13] Nishihira J, Sato M, Tanaka A, Okamatsu M, Azuma T. et al. Maitake mushrooms (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) enhances antibody production in response to influenza vaccination in healthy adult volunteers concurrent with alleviation of common cold symptoms. <em>Functional Foods in Health and Disease</em>. 2017; 7:462-482.<br>[14] Kabir Y, Hoshino T, Komai M, Kimura S. Histopathological changes in spontaneously hypertensive rats after feeding shiitake (<em>Lentinus edodes</em>) and maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) mushroom diets. <em>J Clin Biochem Nutr</em> 1989;6:187-193.<br>[15] Kubo K, Nanba H. The effect of maitake mushrooms on liver and serum lipids. <em>Altern Ther Health Med</em> 1996;2:62-66.<br>[16] Talpur NA, Echard BW, Fan AY, Jaffari O, Bagchi D, Preuss HG. Antihypertensive and metabolic effects of whole Maitake mushroom powder and its fractions in two rat strains. <em>Mol Cell Biochem</em>. 2002;237(1-2):129-136.<br>[17] Balandaykin ME, Zmitrovich IV. Review on chaga medicinal mushroom, <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> (higher basidiomycetes): realm of medicinal applications and approaches on estimating its resource potential. <em>Int J Med Mushrooms</em>. 2015;17(2):95-104.<br>[18] Chung MJ, Chung CK, Jeong Y, Ham SS. Anticancer activity of subfractions containing pure compounds of Chaga mushroom (<em>Inonotus obliquus</em>) extract in human cancer cells and in Balbc/c mice bearing Sarcoma-180 cells. <em>Nutr Res Pract</em>. 2010;4(3):177-182.<br>[19] Mizuno T, Zhuang C, Abe K, Okamoto H, Kiho T, et al. Antitumor and hypoglycemic activities of polysaccharides from the sclerotia and mycelia of <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> (Pers.: Fr.) Pil. (Aphyllophoromycetideae). <em>International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. 1999;1:301-316.<br>[20] Eid JI, Mohanty S, &amp; Das B. Genoprotective effects of Chaga mushroom (<em>Inonotus obliquus</em>) polysaccharides in UVB-exposed embryonic zebrafish (<em>Danio rerio</em>) through coordinated expression of DNA repair genes. <em>bioRxiv</em>. 2020.<br>[21] Softa M, Percoco G, Lati E, &amp; Bony P. Birch sap (<em>Betula alba</em>) and chaga mushroom (<em>Inonotus obliquus</em>) extracts show antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and DNA protection/repair activity <em>in vitro</em>. <em>Journal of Cosmetics</em>, <em>Dermatological Sciences and Applications</em>. 2019;09:188-205.<br>[22] Diao BZ, Jin WR, Yu XJ. Protective effect of polysaccharides from <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> on Streptozotocin-induced diabetic symptoms and their potential mechanisms in rats. <em>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</em>. 2014;2014:841496.<br>[23] Hong KB, Noh DO, Park Y, Suh HJ. Hepatoprotective activity of water extracts from chaga medicinal mushroom, <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> (higher Basidiomycetes) against tert-butyl hydroperoxide-induced oxidative liver injury in Primary cultured rat hepatocytes. <em>Int J Med Mushrooms</em>. 2015;17(11):1069-1076.<br>[24] Janjušević L, Karaman M, Šibul F, et al. The lignicolous fungus <em>Trametes versicolor</em> (L.) Lloyd (1920): a promising natural source of antiradical and AChE inhibitory agents. <em>J Enzyme Inhib Med Chem</em>. 2017;32(1):355-362.<br>[25] Knežević A, Živković L, Stajić M, Vukojević J, Milovanović I, Spremo-Potparević B. Antigenotoxic effect of <em>Trametes</em> spp. extracts against DNA damage on human peripheral white blood cells. <em>Scientific World Journal</em>. 2015;2015:146378.<br>[26] Sekhon BK, Sze DM, Chan WK, et al. PSP activates monocytes in resting human peripheral blood mononuclear cells: immunomodulatory implications for cancer treatment. <em>Food Chem</em>. 2013;138(4):2201-2209.<br>[27] Lu H, Yang Y, Gad E, et al. TLR2 agonist PSK activates human NK cells and enhances the antitumor effect of HER2-targeted monoclonal antibody therapy. <em>Clin Cancer Res</em>. 2011;17(21):6742-6753.<br>[28] Sakamoto J, Morita S, Oba K, et al. Efficacy of adjuvant immunochemotherapy with polysaccharide K for patients with curatively resected colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of centrally randomized controlled clinical trials. <em>Cancer Immunol Immunother</em>. 2006;55(4):404-411.<br>[29] Pallav K, Dowd SE, Villafuerte J, et al. Effects of polysaccharopeptide from <em>Trametes versicolor</em> and amoxicillin on the gut microbiome of healthy volunteers: a randomized clinical trial. <em>Gut Microbes</em>. 2014;5(4):458-467.<br>[30] Eliza WL, Fai CK, Chung LP. Efficacy of Yun Zhi (<em>Coriolus versicolor</em>) on survival in cancer patients: systematic review and meta-analysis. <em>Recent Pat Inflamm Allergy Drug Discov</em>. 2012;6(1):78-87.<br>[31] Tiralongo E, Wee SS, Lea RA. Elderberry supplementation reduces cold duration and symptoms in air-travellers: a randomized, double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial. <em>Nutrients</em>. 2016;8(4):182.<br>[32] Zakay-Rones Z, Thom E, Wollan T, Wadstein J. Randomized study of the efficacy and safety of oral elderberry extract in the treatment of influenza A and B virus infections. <em>J Int Med Res</em>. 2004;32(2):132-140.<br>[33] Carr AC, Maggini S. Vitamin C and immune function. <em>Nutrients</em>. 2017;9(11):1211.<br>[34] Wang TJ, Pencina MJ, Booth SL, et al. Vitamin D deficiency and risk of cardiovascular disease. <em>Circulation</em>. 2008;117(4):503-511.<br>[35] Urashima M, Segawa T, Okazaki M, Kurihara M, Wada Y, Ida H. Randomized trial of vitamin D supplementation to prevent seasonal influenza A in schoolchildren. <em>Am J Clin Nutr</em>. 2010;91(5):1255-1260.<br>[36] Jorde R, Sneve M, Figenschau Y, Svartberg J, Waterloo K. Effects of vitamin D supplementation on symptoms of depression in overweight and obese subjects: randomized double-blind trial. <em>J Intern Med</em>. 2008;264(6):599-609.<br>[37] Mocchegiani E, Giacconi R, Cipriano C, Malavolta M. NK and NKT cells in aging and longevity: role of zinc and metallothioneins. <em>J Clin Immunol</em>. 2009;29(4):416-42 </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/the-magic-behind-mikes-mushroom-mix</id>
    <published>2021-02-05T12:40:16-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-02-05T12:40:18-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/the-magic-behind-mikes-mushroom-mix"/>
    <title>The Magic Behind Mike&apos;s Mushroom Mix</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<strong>What Is It?</strong><br>Powerful functional mushroom blend to keep your body balanced and optimized to perform all day, every day.<br> <br><strong>What’s In It?</strong><br>Ten of the most renowned functional mushrooms combined into an all-around daily supplement.  
<ul>
<li>
<em>Agarikon - </em>for anti-inflammatory, antiviral abilities</li>
<li>Antrodia - to support live tonic</li>
<li>
<em>Chaga -</em> to fight harmful bacteria and viruses</li>
<li>
<em>Cordyceps - </em>natural energy booster</li>
<li>
<em>King Trumpets - </em>to lower cholesterol, help manage diabetes</li>
<li>
<em>Lion’s Mane - </em>for cognition function and memory support</li>
<li>
<em>Maitake </em>- for metabolism support and immune-boosting power.</li>
<li>
<em>Reishi</em> - to enhance immune function and flood the body and mind with tranquility</li>
<li>
<em>Shiitake - </em>to support heart health and skin health</li>
<li>
<em>Turkey tail</em> - for its immune boosting, anti-cancer, and gut health properties</li>
</ul>
<p><strong> </strong><br><strong>What Does It Do?</strong><br>Mike’s Mushroom Mix Anti-inflammatory, anti-viral, and immunity booster. Keeps harmful pathogens in check and your body in an optimal state of balance. With a rich profile of phytochemicals such as polysaccharides, triterpenoids, amino acids, and polyphenols, as well as additions of vitamins B, B-12, C, and D and minerals will support your overall health and keep your body’s defense operating at its full capacity. It also helps with metabolism support, anti-aging, and longevity, and strengthening liver function and gut health.<br> <br><strong>How Does It Work?</strong><br>The Mike’s Mushroom Mix formula provides an intelligent array of fungal molecules demonstrated in the scientific literature to offer wellness properties.</p>
<p>As with many mushrooms,<strong> Agarikon mushrooms </strong>offer strong immune-enhancing properties, including activity against viruses including those in the pox family, herpes simplex virus-1 and 2, influenza A and B, bird influenza (H5N1) and tuberculosis. [1-3] Agarikon also offers antimicrobial properties, showing efficacy against some <em>Bacillus</em>, <em>Staphylococcus</em>, <em>Klebsiella</em>, <em>Aspergillus</em>, and <em>Enterobacte</em>r species. [4,5] Chlorinated coumarins within Agarikon have provided treatment of pulmonary diseases such as tuberculosis and pneumonia. [5] Triterpenoids in Agarikon can inhibit nitric oxide production which is involved in inflammatory diseases including asthma. </p>
<p>The fungus <strong><em>Antrodia cinnamomea</em></strong>, or AC mushroom provides immune-enhancing properties like many of the mushrooms selected for use in Spore products. [6-8] The triterpene methyl antcinate K isolated from <em>A. cinnamomea</em> promotes dendritic cells which are vital leukocytes or white blood cells. [7] Additionally, high-molecular weight polysaccharides from <em>A. cinnamomea</em> have demonstrated adjuvant effects on dendritic cells and in immunotherapy vaccines for cancer. [8] The polysaccharide galactomannan provides an example of an immunostimulatory compound extracted from <em>Antrodia</em> that enhances resistances against bacterial attacks in the early stages of an infection but also lessens the risk of severe infection by lessening the production of pro-inflammatory cytokines. [9]<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Chaga mushrooms </strong>offer anticancer, immune-enhancing, antioxidant, anti-hyperglycemic, and anti-mutagenic (gene-protecting) properties. [10] Chaga contains compounds such as 3β-hydroxy-lanosta-8,24-dien-21-al, inotodiol (a triterpene), and lanosterol and each of these molecules showed effectiveness against multiple cancer cell lines with low toxicity to normal cells. [11] Polysaccharides extracted from chaga have reduced tumor size. [12] Chaga mushrooms also provide immune support, antimutagenic, antimicrobial, and antioxidant activity, and anti-hyperglycemic properties. [10] For example, chaga mushroom dosing led to decreased DNA damage and an improvement in deformed structures in zebrafish exposed to UVB radiation. [13] Chaga antioxidant capability prevented the formation of reactive oxygen species helping lessen oxidative stress induced by UV treatment and reduced the amount of pro-inflammatory cytokines brought about by the radiation. [14] Like reishi mushrooms, chaga aids as an antihyperglycemic agent due to its antioxidative properties and its ability to provide protection against cellular damage. [15] Chaga mushrooms also provide protection against liver injury by eliminating free radicals, inhibiting the leakage of key enzymes from the induced damage, and decreasing malondialdehyde formation. [16]</p>
<p>Traditional uses of <strong>cordyceps mushrooms</strong> include promotion of health, longevity, and athletic power and endurance. [17] In 1993, Chinese runners who had ingested cordyceps achieved records in several running events, thrusting these mushrooms on the world stage as potential energy enhancers. Thus, cordyceps is used in Spore products to provide a burst of energy. One study demonstrated that, with or without exercising, cordyceps improved exercise endurance by activating skeletal muscle metabolic regulators and increasing antioxidants. [17] A double-blind, placebo-controlled trial also demonstrated these findings in older adults (ages 50-75 years) who ingested 333 mg of dried mushrooms. [18] Aerobic performance improved and the ingestion of the mushrooms pointed to resistance to fatigue. </p>
<p>Polysaccharides in <strong>king trumpet mushrooms</strong> provide powerful antioxidants that help scavenge free radicals and promote key antioxidant enzymes like superoxide dismutase that help reduce oxidative stress. [19] These polysaccharides also provide anti-tumor effects through immune system modulation. Two such polysaccharides called PEP-1 and PEP-2 demonstrated the ability to provoke apoptosis. [20] Like other mushrooms that exhibit anti-cancer properties, king trumpet polysaccharides act on the host organism’s immune system, augmenting its ability to fend off the invaders in part by stimulating the response of natural killer cells helping them be better killer. [21]</p>
<p>Polysaccharides in <strong>lion’s mane mushrooms </strong>can promote neuronal health. [22] An extract of lion’s mane, for example, stimulated the production of nerve growth factor which is involved in regulating and maintaining specific neurons. [23] Mice given lion’s mane mushrooms in their feed (5% w/w) for 7 days had increased nerve growth factor mRNA expression in the hippocampus, a region of the brain instrumental in learning and memory. [24] These properties have been implicated in lion’s mane’s ability to reduce neurodegenerative-induced cell death. [25] In a double-blind study of Japanese men and women aged 50-80 and diagnosed with mild cognitive impairment. [26] The study participants consumed 250 mg of mushroom tablets containing 96% lion’s mane 3 times per day for 16 weeks. Cognitive function scores increased with the timeframe that the participants ingested the mushrooms. </p>
<p>Glucans from <em>Grifola frondosa</em> or <strong>maitake mushrooms</strong> provide strong antioxidant and immune-supporting properties [27-29], providing evidence for anti-aging capabilities. Antioxidative properties worked by augmenting key enzymes like superoxide dismutase and glutathione peroxidase activity, which in turn, catalyze the destruction of the superoxide radical and reduce lipid hydroperoxides to alcohols and hydrogen peroxide to water, respectively. Additionally, these glucans increased interleukine-2 (IL-2) production, an immunocytokine that has strong immune-enhancing properties providing the most effective cytokine for T cell biology (a type of white blood cell), as well as the ability to boost the activity of natural killer cells, another type of lymphocyte vital to our immune systems. Malondialdehyde (a common marker for oxidative stress) content in the liver was reduced, further demonstrating maitake’s antioxidant properties. [28] What’s more, α-glucan from maitake offers anti-tumor activity by promoting the production of cells that enhance our immune systems like tumor necrosis factor α, different interleukins, and through macrophage cell activation. [30] And a human clinical trial showed that maitake mushrooms led to increased antibodies in in response to influenza type A virus H1N1 after study participants took 20 maitake tablets per day. [31] Maitake mushrooms also help improve metabolism, showing increased fat metabolism [32,33] and other age-related metabolic issues such as glucose/insulin metabolism (e.g., hyperglycemia) [34].<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Reishi mushrooms</strong>, for example, called “the mushroom of immortality” [35], have been studied for their immune-enhancing, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-tumor, and antimicrobial properties. [36] <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> – the species relevant to this formula – is reported to have over 400 bioactive compounds mostly comprised of polysaccharides and triterpenoids. The immune-enhancing properties of reishi polysaccharides work by increasing the amounts of key immune cells such as natural killer, B-lymphocyte, T-lymphocyte white blood cells, dendritic cells, phagocytes that protect our bodies from foreign particles and may also be examples of white blood cells. A more robust immune system, in turn, is vital in cancer treatment, and reishi polysaccharides stimulate cancer resistance through their immune-enhancing capabilities, by inducing apoptosis (cell death) of cancerous cells, and through their anti-cancer preventing activity. [37,38] Reishi triterpenes offer anti-cancer properties as well, through their toxicity to cancer cells, anti-metastatic effects, and induction of apoptosis. [37-39] Reishi polysaccharides and triterpenes have shown antioxidant and antimicrobial properties, with the terpenes presenting higher antioxidative capacities. The mushroom’s polysaccharides have also demonstrated anti-aging properties through their ability to protect fibroblasts (cells that provides structural framework in mammalian tissue and aids wound healing) from harmful ultraviolet B (UVB) radiation. [40] The UVB treated cells revealed increased signs of aging and reactive oxygen species and decreased cell viability, but when cells were treated with UVB <em>and</em> reishi polysaccharides, the UVB reactive oxygen species were eliminated. Reishi mushrooms also have been used for their sedative, calming properties. In one study, a reishi extract showed similar anti-anxiety properties as the pharmaceutical drug diazepam. [41] Reishi powder also diminished fatigue, anxiety, and depression, and provided a better quality of life in 48 breast cancer survivors. [42]</p>
<p>The consumption of <strong><em>shiitake mushrooms</em> </strong>has been shown to improve our immune systems. [43-45] Shiitake’s immune-enhancing properties stem from several mechanisms including an increase in key immune cells such as natural killer T cells. [43] Beta-glucans in shiitake mushrooms are known to interact with receptors on several types of immune cells. The mushrooms offer anti-tumor properties, not because they directly engage the tumor, but because they activate immune responses in the host. [45] The polysaccharide lentinan, for example, acts as a host defense potentiators which help hosts defend against various types of cancer. Shiitakes are also known to improve gut health and have led to diminished levels of C-reactive protein, a common marker for inflammation. </p>
<p>Like the other mushrooms in Mike’s Mushroom Mix, <strong>turkey tail mushrooms </strong>provide strong antioxidant properties. [46] In addition to polysaccharides and triterpenes, turkey tail offers many phenolic species like flavonols and flavonoids like quercetin. And also like other mushrooms within Mike’s Mushroom Mix, turkey tail mushrooms demonstrate genoprotective capabilities. [47] In addition to its polysaccharides, turkey tail contains polysaccharides that are also bound to proteins in complexes called polysaccharopeptides. Krestin (PSK) and polysaccharide peptide (PSP) are two such molecules that have strong immune-enhancing properties. PSP, for example, has been shown to increase white blood cells [48] and PSK stimulates natural killer immune cells. [49] PSK has also shown powerful anticancer properties, with one study measuring an increased survival in colon cancer patients who received PSK as an adjuvant immunochemotherapy. [50] An adjuvant therapy seeks to keep the cancer from coming back post-treatment, and an immunotherapy targets the immune system. Turkey tail mushrooms also increase gut health since they contain prebiotics. One study found that consuming 3.6 g per day of PSP from turkey tail led to beneficial microbiome changes and reduced the growth of infectious bacteria such as <em>E. coli </em>and <em>Shigella</em>. [51] Another study measured higher concentrations of beneficial gut bacteria such as <em>Bifidobacterium </em>and <em>Lactobacillus </em>while detrimental bacteria like <em>Clostridium</em> and <em>Staphylococcus</em> were lessened. [52]<br> <br>These statements have not been evaluated by the Food &amp; Drug Administration. This product is not intended to diagnose, treat, cure, or prevent any disease.<br><strong><em> </em></strong><br><strong>References</strong><br>[1] Stamets P. Antipox properties of <em>Fomitopsis officinalis</em> (Vill.: Fr.) Bond. et Singer (Agarikon) from the Pacific Northwest of North America. <em>International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. 2005;7:495-506.<br>[2] Stamets P. Medicinal polypores of the forests of North America: screening for novel antiviral activity. <em>International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. 2005;7:362.<br>[3] Teplyakova TV, Psurtseva NV, Kosogova TA, Mazurkova NA, Khanin VA, Vlasenko VA. Antiviral activity of polyporoid mushrooms (higher Basidiomycetes) from Altai Mountains (Russia). <em>Int J Med Mushrooms</em>. 2012;14(1):37-45.<br>[4] Girometta C. Antimicrobial properties of <em>Fomitopsis officinalis</em> in the light of its bioactive metabolites: a review. <em>Mycology</em>. 2018;10(1):32-39. <br>[5] Elkhateeb W, Daba G, Elnahas M, &amp; Thomas P. <em>Fomitopsis officinalis</em> mushroom: ancient gold mine of functional components and biological activities for modern medicine. <em>Egyptian Pharmaceutical Journal</em>. 2019;18:285-289.<br>[6] Lin IY, Pan MH, Lai CS, et al. CCM111, the water extract of <em>Antrodia cinnamomea</em>, regulates immune-related activity through STAT3 and NF-κB pathways. <em>Sci Rep</em>. 2017;7(1):4862.<br>[7] Yu YL, Chen IH, Shen KY, et al. A triterpenoid methyl antcinate K isolated from <em>Antrodia cinnamomea</em> promotes dendritic cell activation and Th2 differentiation. <em>Eur J Immunol</em>. 2009;39(9):2482-2491.<br>[8] Lin CC, Pan IH, Li YR, et al. The adjuvant effects of high-molecule-weight polysaccharides purified from <em>Antrodia cinnamomea</em> on dendritic cell function and DNA vaccines. <em>PLoS One</em>. 2015;10(2):e0116191.             <br>[9] Perera N, Yang FL, Lu YT, Li LH, Hua KF, Wu SH. <em>Antrodia cinnamomea</em> galactomannan elicits immuno-stimulatory activity through toll-like receptor 4. <em>Int J Biol Sci</em>. 2018;14(10):1378-1388.<br>[10] Balandaykin ME, Zmitrovich IV. Review on chaga medicinal mushroom, <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> (higher basidiomycetes): realm of medicinal applications and approaches on estimating its resource potential. <em>Int J Med Mushrooms</em>. 2015;17(2):95-104.<br>[11] Chung MJ, Chung CK, Jeong Y, Ham SS. Anticancer activity of subfractions containing pure compounds of Chaga mushroom (<em>Inonotus obliquus</em>) extract in human cancer cells and in Balbc/c mice bearing Sarcoma-180 cells. <em>Nutr Res Pract</em>. 2010;4(3):177-182.<br>[12] Mizuno T, Zhuang C, Abe K, Okamoto H, Kiho T, et al. Antitumor and hypoglycemic activities of polysaccharides from the sclerotia and mycelia of <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> (Pers.: Fr.) Pil. (Aphyllophoromycetideae). <em>International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. 1999;1:301-316.<br>[13] Eid JI, Mohanty S, &amp; Das B. Genoprotective effects of Chaga mushroom (<em>Inonotus obliquus</em>) polysaccharides in UVB-exposed embryonic zebrafish (<em>Danio rerio</em>) through coordinated expression of DNA repair genes. <em>bioRxiv</em>. 2020.<br>[14] Softa M, Percoco G, Lati E, &amp; Bony P. Birch sap (<em>Betula alba</em>) and chaga mushroom (<em>Inonotus obliquus</em>) extracts show antioxidant, anti-inflammatory and DNA protection/repair activity <em>in vitro</em>. <em>Journal of Cosmetics</em>, <em>Dermatological Sciences and Applications</em>. 2019;09:188-205.<br>[15] Diao BZ, Jin WR, Yu XJ. Protective effect of polysaccharides from <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> on Streptozotocin-induced diabetic symptoms and their potential mechanisms in rats. <em>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</em>. 2014;2014:841496.<br>[16] Hong KB, Noh DO, Park Y, Suh HJ. Hepatoprotective activity of water extracts from chaga medicinal mushroom, <em>Inonotus obliquus</em> (higher Basidiomycetes) against tert-butyl hydroperoxide-induced oxidative liver injury in Primary cultured rat hepatocytes. <em>Int J Med Mushrooms</em>. 2015;17(11):1069-1076.<br>[17] Kumar R, Negi PS, Singh B, Ilavazhagan G, Bhargava K, Sethy NK. <em>Cordyceps sinensis</em> promotes exercise endurance capacity of rats by activating skeletal muscle metabolic regulators. <em>J Ethnopharmacol</em>. 2011;136(1):260-266.<br>[18] Chen S, Li Z, Krochmal R, Abrazado M, Kim W, Cooper CB. Effect of Cs-4 (<em>Cordyceps sinensis</em>) on exercise performance in healthy older subjects: a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. <em>J Altern Complement Med</em>. 2010;16(5):585-590.<br>[19] Zhang B, Li Y, Zhang F, Linhardt RJ, Zeng G, Zhang A. Extraction, structure, and bioactivities of the polysaccharides from <em>Pleurotus eryngii</em>: A review. <em>Int J Biol Macromol</em>. 2020;150:1342-1347.<br>[20] Ren D, Wang N, Guo J, Yuan L, Yang X. Chemical characterization of <em>Pleurotus eryngii</em> polysaccharide and its tumor-inhibitory effects against human hepatoblastoma HepG-2 cells. <em>Carbohydr Polym</em>. 2016;138:123-133.<br>[21] Yang Z, Xu J, Fu Q, et al. Antitumor activity of a polysaccharide from <em>Pleurotus eryngii</em> on mice bearing renal cancer. <em>Carbohydr Polym</em>. 2013;95(2):615-620.<br>[22] Park YS, Lee HS, Won MH, Lee JH, Lee SY, Lee HY. Effect of an exo-polysaccharide from the culture broth of <em>Hericium erinaceus</em> on enhancement of growth and differentiation of rat adrenal nerve cells. <em>Cytotechnology</em>. 2002;39(3):155-162.<br>[23] Kawagishi H, Shimada A, Shirai R, Okamoto K, Ojima F, Sakamoto H, et al. Erinacines A, B, and C, strong stimulators of nerve growth factor (NGF)-synthesis, from the mycelia of <em>Hericium erinaceum</em>. <em>Tetrahedron Lett</em>. 1994;35:1569–72.<br>[24] Mori K, Obara Y, Hirota M, et al. Nerve growth factor-inducing activity of <em>Hericium erinaceus</em> in 1321N1 human astrocytoma cells. <em>Biol Pharm Bull</em>. 2008;31(9):1727-1732.<br>[25] Nagai K, Chiba A, Nishino T, Kubota T, Kawagishi H. Dilinoleoyl-phosphatidylethanolamine from <em>Hericium erinaceum</em> protects against ER stress-dependent Neuro2a cell death via protein kinase C pathway. <em>J Nutr Biochem</em>. 2006;17:525–30.<br>[26] Mori K, Inatomi S, Ouchi K, Azumi Y, Tuchida T. Improving effects of the mushroom Yamabushitake (<em>Hericium erinaceus</em>) on mild cognitive impairment: a double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial. <em>Phytother Res</em>. 2009;23(3):367-372.<br>[27] Vetvicka V, Vetvickova J. Immune-enhancing effects of Maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) and Shiitake (<em>Lentinula edodes</em>) extracts. <em>Ann Transl Med</em>. 2014;2(2):14.<br>[28] Hong L, Weiyub W, Qina W, Shuzhena G, and Lebin W. Antioxidant and immunomodulatory effects of a a-glucan from fruit body of maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>). <em>Food and Agricultural Immunology</em>. 2013;24(4):409-418.<br>[29] Yeh JY, Hsieh LH, Wu KT, Tsai CF. Antioxidant properties and antioxidant compounds of various extracts from the edible basidiomycete <em>Grifola frondosa</em> (Maitake). <em>Molecules</em>. 2011;16(4):3197-3211.<br>[30] Masuda Y, Nakayama Y, Tanaka A, Naito K, Konishi M. Antitumor activity of orally administered maitake α-glucan by stimulating antitumor immune response in murine tumor. <em>PLoS One</em>. 2017;12(3):e0173621.<br>[31] Nishihira J, Sato M, Tanaka A, Okamatsu M, Azuma T. et al. Maitake mushrooms (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) enhances antibody production in response to influenza vaccination in healthy adult volunteers concurrent with alleviation of common cold symptoms. <em>Functional Foods in Health and Disease</em>. 2017; 7:462-482.<br>[32] Kabir Y, Hoshino T, Komai M, Kimura S. Histopathological changes in spontaneously hypertensive rats after feeding shiitake (<em>Lentinus edodes</em>) and maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) mushroom diets. <em>J Clin Biochem Nutr</em> 1989;6:187-193.<br>[33] Kubo K, Nanba H. The effect of maitake mushrooms on liver and serum lipids. <em>Altern Ther Health Med</em> 1996;2:62-66.<br>[34] Talpur NA, Echard BW, Fan AY, Jaffari O, Bagchi D, Preuss HG. Antihypertensive and metabolic effects of whole Maitake mushroom powder and its fractions in two rat strains. <em>Mol Cell Biochem</em>. 2002;237(1-2):129-136.<br>[35] Stamets P. (2000). <em>Growing Gourmet and Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. Berkeley, CA: Ten Speed Press.<br>[36] Sanodiya BS, Thakur GS, Baghel RK, Prasad GB, Bisen PS. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em>: a potent pharmacological macrofungus. <em>Curr Pharm Biotechnol</em>. 2009;10(8):717-742.<br>[37] Cör D, Knez Ž, Knez Hrnčič M. Antitumour, antimicrobial, antioxidant and antiacetylcholinesterase effect of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> terpenoids and polysaccharides: A review. <em>Molecules</em>. 2018;23(3):649.<br>[38] Paterson R.R.M. Ganoderma—A therapeutic fungal biofactory. <em>Phytochemistry</em>. 2006;68:1985–2001.<br>[39] Sohretoglu D, Huang S. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> polysaccharides as an anti-cancer agent. <em>Anticancer Agents Med Chem</em>. 2018;18(5):667-674.<br>[40] Zeng Q, Zhou F, Lei L, et al. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> polysaccharides protect fibroblasts against UVB-induced photoaging. <em>Mol Med Rep</em>. 2017;15(1):111-116.<br>[41] Ali N, Muhammad A, &amp; Akbar S.A. Anxiolytic-like activity of ethanol extract of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> (Reishi) in mice. <em>International Journal of Medical Research and Health Sciences</em>. 2016;5:57-60.<br>[42] Zhao H, Zhang Q, Zhao L, Huang X, Wang J, Kang X. Spore powder of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> improves cancer-related fatigue in breast cancer patients undergoing endocrine therapy: A Pilot Clinical Trial. <em>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</em>. 2012;2012:809614.<br>[43] Dai X, Stanilka JM, Rowe CA, et al. Consuming <em>Lentinula edodes</em> (Shiitake) mushrooms daily improves human immunity: a randomized dietary intervention in healthy young adults. <em>J Am Coll Nutr</em>. 2015;34(6):478-487.<br>[44] Nisar J, Mustafa I, Anwar H, et al. Shiitake culinary-medicinal mushroom, <em>Lentinus edodes</em> (Agaricomycetes): a species with antioxidant, immunomodulatory, and hepatoprotective activities in hypercholesterolemic rats. <em>Int J Med Mushrooms</em>. 2017;19(11):981-990.<br>[45] Wasser S. Shiitake (<em>Lentinus edodes</em>). In Coates P, Blackman MR, Betz J, Cragg GM, Levine M, Moss J, &amp; White JD. <em>Encyclopedia of Dietary Supplements</em>. 2010.<br>[46] Janjušević L, Karaman M, Šibul F, et al. The lignicolous fungus <em>Trametes versicolor</em> (L.) Lloyd (1920): a promising natural source of antiradical and AChE inhibitory agents. <em>J Enzyme Inhib Med Chem</em>. 2017;32(1):355-362.<br>[47] Knežević A, Živković L, Stajić M, Vukojević J, Milovanović I, Spremo-Potparević B. Antigenotoxic effect of <em>Trametes</em> spp. extracts against DNA damage on human peripheral white blood cells. <em>Scientific World Journal</em>. 2015;2015:146378.<br>[48] Sekhon BK, Sze DM, Chan WK, et al. PSP activates monocytes in resting human peripheral blood mononuclear cells: immunomodulatory implications for cancer treatment. <em>Food Chem</em>. 2013;138(4):2201-2209.<br>[49] Lu H, Yang Y, Gad E, et al. TLR2 agonist PSK activates human NK cells and enhances the antitumor effect of HER2-targeted monoclonal antibody therapy. <em>Clin Cancer Res</em>. 2011;17(21):6742-6753.<br>[50] Sakamoto J, Morita S, Oba K, et al. Efficacy of adjuvant immunochemotherapy with polysaccharide K for patients with curatively resected colorectal cancer: a meta-analysis of centrally randomized controlled clinical trials. <em>Cancer Immunol Immunother</em>. 2006;55(4):404-411.<br>[51] Pallav K, Dowd SE, Villafuerte J, et al. Effects of polysaccharopeptide from <em>Trametes versicolor</em> and amoxicillin on the gut microbiome of healthy volunteers: a randomized clinical trial. <em>Gut Microbes</em>. 2014;5(4):458-467.<br>[52] Eliza WL, Fai CK, Chung LP. Efficacy of Yun Zhi (<em>Coriolus versicolor</em>) on survival in cancer patients: systematic review and meta-analysis. <em>Recent Pat Inflamm Allergy Drug Discov</em>. 2012;6(1):78-87.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/whats-inside-our-focus-performance</id>
    <published>2021-02-05T12:37:39-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-02-05T12:37:41-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/whats-inside-our-focus-performance"/>
    <title>What&apos;s Inside Our Focus Performance</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>What Is It?</strong><br>This nootropic blend combines the cognitive boosting power of Lion’s Mane with sustained energy from Cordyceps to help you unlock your peak mental performance each day.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>What’s In It?</strong><br>Combines the cognitive boosting power of Lion’s Mane, the sustained energy from Cordyceps, and supported by Ashwagandha and Gingko Biloba to provide increased cognitive enhancement and a mood-stabilizing effect: </p>
<ul>
<li>
<em>Lion’s mane </em>- to help with cognitive function, memory support, and immune function</li>
<li>
<em>Cordyceps </em>- for all-natural energy production and increase Vo2 Max</li>
<li>
<em>Ashwagandha </em>- to enhance immune function and mood stabilizing properties</li>
<li>
<em>Ginkgo Biloba - </em>for cognitive function, mental awareness</li>
</ul>
<p> <br><strong>What Does It Do?</strong><br>Focus Performance improves working memory, expanded creativity, and complete support for your brain’s neurological functioning.  On top of all that, we added Lion’s Mane proven neuroprotective benefits.  The formulation offers a rich profile of phytochemicals such as polysaccharides, triterpenoids, amino acids, and polyphenols, as well as additions of vitamins B, B-12, C, and D and minerals will support your overall health.<br> <br><strong>How Does It Work?</strong><br>The Focus Performance formula provides an intelligent array of fungal molecules demonstrated in the scientific literature to offer wellness properties.</p>
<p>Polysaccharides in <strong>lion’s mane mushrooms </strong>can promote neuronal health. [1] An extract of lion’s mane, for example, stimulated the production of nerve growth factor which is involved in regulating and maintaining specific neurons. [2] Mice given lion’s mane mushrooms in their feed (5% w/w) for 7 days had increased nerve growth factor mRNA expression in the hippocampus, a region of the brain instrumental in learning and memory. [3] These properties have been implicated in lion’s mane’s ability to reduce neurodegenerative-induced cell death. [4] In a double-blind study of Japanese men and women aged 50-80 and diagnosed with mild cognitive impairment. [5] The study participants consumed 250 mg of mushroom tablets containing 96% lion’s mane 3 times per day for 16 weeks. Cognitive function scores increased with the timeframe that the participants ingested the mushrooms. </p>
<p>Traditional uses of <strong>cordyceps mushrooms</strong> include promotion of health, longevity, and athletic power and endurance. [6] In 1993, Chinese runners who had ingested cordyceps achieved records in several running events, thrusting these mushrooms on the world stage as potential energy enhancers. Thus, cordyceps is used in Spore products to provide a burst of energy. One study demonstrated that, with or without exercising, cordyceps improved exercise endurance by activating skeletal muscle metabolic regulators and increasing antioxidants. [6] A double-blind, placebo-controlled trial also demonstrated these findings in older adults (ages 50-75 years) who ingested 333 mg of dried mushrooms. [7] Aerobic performance improved and the ingestion of the mushrooms pointed to resistance to fatigue. <br>The shrub knows as<strong> Ashwagandha </strong>(<em>Withania somnifera</em>) is a recurrent remedy in Ayurvedic medicine. It is used to promote “youthful vigour” by augmenting muscle strength, endurance, and overall health. [8] The withanolides within ashwagandha bestow intrinsic therapeutic properties including anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-cancer, anti-anxiety, and immune-enhancing effects. [9] Pre-clinical models have shown anti-anxiety, anti-depressive, and neuroprotective properties. [10] A 60-day, double-blind clinical trial demonstrated these effects in humans. [9] Contrasted with the study participants who ingested the placebo, those who consumed ashwagandha daily experienced reductions in cortisol levels, anxiety, and stress. Additionally, testosterone levels increased in male participants. The combination of ashwagandha and maitake extracts demonstrated a synergy for enhancing immune responses to stress via phagocytosis (ingestion of bacteria or other foreign invaders by phagocytes) and increased cytokine levels. [11] While the ashwagandha extract worked well on its own, the beta-glucans within the maitake extract potentiated the immune-enhancing activity.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Ginkgo Biloba (Leaf)</strong> is often associated with mental health and cognition. Cognitive decline is associated with neurodegenerative diseases like Alzheimer’s disease and dementia, and gingko biloba extract has shown promise in depressive patients diagnosed with Alzheimer’s disease. [12] An extract of gingko biloba contains flavonoids, terpene lactones, and ginkgolic acids that have provided increased neuroplasticity (the brain's ability to adapt or change), prevented brain edema (swelling), and offered neuroprotection. [13-15] A 2016 meta-analysis of ten reviews of ginkgo biloba extract concluded that “medication with [gingko biloba extracts] showed improvement in cognition and daily activities.” [15] Other reviews have provided similar conclusions. [16] In fact, the <em>Physician’s Desk Reference for Herbal Medicines</em> suggests taking 120 mg of dry extract divided up in multiple doses. [17]<br> <br>These statements have not been evaluated by the Food &amp; Drug Administration. This product is not intended to diagnose, treat, cure, or prevent any disease.<br><strong> </strong><br><strong>References</strong><br>[1] Park YS, Lee HS, Won MH, Lee JH, Lee SY, Lee HY. Effect of an exo-polysaccharide from the culture broth of <em>Hericium erinaceus</em> on enhancement of growth and differentiation of rat adrenal nerve cells. <em>Cytotechnology</em>. 2002;39(3):155-162.<br>[2] Kawagishi H, Shimada A, Shirai R, Okamoto K, Ojima F, Sakamoto H, et al. Erinacines A, B, and C, strong stimulators of nerve growth factor (NGF)-synthesis, from the mycelia of <em>Hericium erinaceum</em>. <em>Tetrahedron Lett</em>. 1994;35:1569–72.<br>[3] Mori K, Obara Y, Hirota M, et al. Nerve growth factor-inducing activity of <em>Hericium erinaceus</em> in 1321N1 human astrocytoma cells. <em>Biol Pharm Bull</em>. 2008;31(9):1727-1732.<br>[4] Nagai K, Chiba A, Nishino T, Kubota T, Kawagishi H. Dilinoleoyl-phosphatidylethanolamine from <em>Hericium erinaceum</em> protects against ER stress-dependent Neuro2a cell death via protein kinase C pathway. <em>J Nutr Biochem</em>. 2006;17:525–30.<br>[5] Mori K, Inatomi S, Ouchi K, Azumi Y, Tuchida T. Improving effects of the mushroom Yamabushitake (<em>Hericium erinaceus</em>) on mild cognitive impairment: a double-blind placebo-controlled clinical trial. <em>Phytother Res</em>. 2009;23(3):367-372.<br>[6] Kumar R, Negi PS, Singh B, Ilavazhagan G, Bhargava K, Sethy NK. <em>Cordyceps sinensis</em> promotes exercise endurance capacity of rats by activating skeletal muscle metabolic regulators. <em>J Ethnopharmacol</em>. 2011;136(1):260-266.<br>[7] Chen S, Li Z, Krochmal R, Abrazado M, Kim W, Cooper CB. Effect of Cs-4 (<em>Cordyceps sinensis</em>) on exercise performance in healthy older subjects: a double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. <em>J Altern Complement Med</em>. 2010;16(5):585-590.<br>[8] Kulkarni SK, Dhir A. <em>Withania somnifera</em>: an Indian ginseng. <em>Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatry</em> 2008;32:1093–105.<br>[9] Lopresti AL, Smith SJ, Malvi H, Kodgule R. An investigation into the stress-relieving and pharmacological actions of an ashwagandha (<em>Withania somnifera</em>) extract: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. <em>Medicine</em> (Baltimore). 2019;98(37):e17186.<br>[10] Bhattacharya SK, Bhattacharya A, Sairam K, Ghosal S. Anxiolytic-antidepressant activity of <em>Withania somnifera</em> glycowithanolides: an experimental study. <em>Phytomedicine</em>. 2000;7(6):463-469.<br>[11] Vetvicka V, Vetvickova J. Immune enhancing effects of WB365, a novel combination of Ashwagandha (<em>Withania somnifera</em>) and Maitake (<em>Grifola frondosa</em>) extracts. <em>N Am J Med Sci</em>. 2011;3(7):320-324.<br>[12] DeFeudis FV, Drieu K. Ginkgo biloba extract (EGb 761) and CNS functions: basic studies and clinical applications. <em>Curr Drug Targets</em>. 2000;1(1):25-58.<br>[13] Tchantchou F, Xu Y, Wu Y, Christen Y, Luo Y. EGb 761 enhances adult hippocampal neurogenesis and phosphorylation of CREB in transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer's disease. <em>FASEB J</em>. 2007;21(10):2400-2408.<br>[14] Yoshitake T, Yoshitake S, Kehr J. The <em>Ginkgo biloba</em> extract EGb 761(R) and its main constituent flavonoids and ginkgolides increase extracellular dopamine levels in the rat prefrontal cortex. <em>Br J Pharmacol</em>. 2010;159(3):659-668.<br>[15] Zhang HF, Huang LB, Zhong YB, et al. An overview of systematic reviews of <em>Ginkgo biloba</em> extracts for mild cognitive impairment and dementia. <em>Front Aging Neurosci</em>. 2016;8:276.<br>[16] Diamond BJ, Shiflett SC, Feiwel N, et al. <em>Ginkgo biloba</em> extract: mechanisms and clinical indications. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2000;81(5):668-678.<br>[17] <em>Physician’s Desk Reference (PDR) for Herbal Medicines</em>. 1st ed. Montvale (NJ): Medical Economics Company; 1998.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/all-about-our-chill-out-formulation</id>
    <published>2021-02-05T12:32:22-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-02-05T12:36:27-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/all-about-our-chill-out-formulation"/>
    <title>All About Our Chill Out Formulation</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<strong>What Is It?</strong><br>This adaptogenic blend contains a plethora of antioxidants, vitamins, and minerals for calming, anti-stress blend that offers exactly what you need to slip into that sweet relaxation at the end of the day.<br> <br><strong>What’s In It?</strong><br>This formula combines the power of the Reishi mushroom with natural herbs like chamomile, lemon balm, and valerian root.
<ul>
<li>
<em>Reishi </em>- to enhance immune function and flood the body and mind with tranquility.</li>
<li>
<em>Chamomile </em>- used as a mild sedative to calm nerves</li>
<li>
<em>Lemon Balm </em>- can help reduce anxiety</li>
<li>
<em>Passionflower - </em>helps calm the mind and support sleep cycle</li>
<li>
<em>Valerian Root </em>- to help with sleep disorders and migraines </li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What Does It Do?</strong><br>Chill Out offers a dense well rounded nutritional profile that allows customers to enjoy this blend in the evening and flood your body with tranquility so you’re ready to enjoy deep, restorative sleep every night.<br> <br><strong>How Does It Work?</strong><br>The Chill Out formula provides an intelligent array of fungal molecules demonstrated in the scientific literature to offer wellness properties.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p><strong>Reishi mushrooms</strong>, for example, called “the mushroom of immortality” [1], have been studied for their immune-enhancing, anti-inflammatory, antioxidant, anti-tumor, and antimicrobial properties. [2] <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> – the species relevant to this formula – is reported to have over 400 bioactive compounds mostly comprised of polysaccharides and triterpenoids. The immune-enhancing properties of reishi polysaccharides work by increasing the amounts of key immune cells such as natural killer, B-lymphocyte, T-lymphocyte white blood cells, dendritic cells, phagocytes that protect our bodies from foreign particles and may also be examples of white blood cells. A more robust immune system, in turn, is vital in cancer treatment, and reishi polysaccharides stimulate cancer resistance through their immune-enhancing capabilities, by inducing apoptosis (cell death) of cancerous cells, and through their anti-cancer preventing activity. [3,4] Reishi triterpenes offer anti-cancer properties as well, through their toxicity to cancer cells, anti-metastatic effects, and induction of apoptosis. [3-5] Reishi polysaccharides and triterpenes have shown antioxidant and antimicrobial properties, with the terpenes presenting higher antioxidative capacities. The mushroom’s polysaccharides have also demonstrated anti-aging properties through their ability to protect fibroblasts (cells that provides structural framework in mammalian tissue and aids wound healing) from harmful ultraviolet B (UVB) radiation. [6] The UVB treated cells revealed increased signs of aging and reactive oxygen species and decreased cell viability, but when cells were treated with UVB <em>and</em> reishi polysaccharides, the UVB reactive oxygen species were eliminated. Reishi mushrooms also have been used for their sedative, calming properties. In one study, a reishi extract showed similar anti-anxiety properties as the pharmaceutical drug diazepam. [7] Reishi powder also diminished fatigue, anxiety, and depression, and provided a better quality of life in 48 breast cancer survivors. [8]</p>
<p>The elegance of <strong>chamomile </strong>cannot be understated. Chamomile contains the terpene alcohol called alpha-bisabolol that imparts significant anti-cancer properties. [9] In addition, chamomile offers well-known anxiolytic, calming properties. Sedative properties have been linked to the flavonoid apigenin. [10] Pre-clinical studies have demonstrated anti-convulsant properties and a depression of the central nervous system. [11] Chamomile tea exhibited a sedative activity similar to benzodiazepines, a class of drugs used in treating anxiety and depression. [12] In a clinical trial, chamomile also showed anxiolytic activity in patients with general anxiety disorder. [13]</p>
<p>The herb <strong>Lemon Balm </strong>offers another option for stress relief. [14] Records of the use of lemon balm have existed for at least a millennium. A drink containing 300 mg of lemon balm conferred anxiolytic properties as well as providing a better working memory at test durations of 1- and 3-hours after ingestion, demonstrating sustained effects like benzodiazepines. Pre-clinical studies have shown that a lemon balm extract provides similar antidepressant and anxiolytic activity as diazepam, a common drug used to treat anxiety. [15] A double-blind clinical trial involving 24 participants evaluated 3 doses (600, 1200, 1800 mg) of a product containing lemon balm and valerian. [16] The 600 mg dose led to decreased anxiety as demonstrated by the Defined Intensity Stressor Simulation, a series of tasks meant to invoke anxiety.</p>
<p>The <strong>Passionflower </strong>plant offers a tempting fruit and another source of natural medicine. Passionflower’s anxiolytic properties have been known through folklore and through clinical trials. [17] The clinical trial considered 36 patients diagnosed with general anxiety disorder. Eighteen of the patients received 45 drops of passionflower extract per day while the others received oxazepam, a benzodiazepine used to treat anxiety. There were no significant differences between the effects of the natural substance and pharmaceutical drug, highlighting the power of nature. Another study considered the sleep habits of 41 participants who either ingested passionflower or a placebo tea. [18] The participants who ingested passionflower reported better ratings of sleep quality compared to those who received the placebo. A meta-analysis of nine clinical trials found similar results. [19]</p>
<p><strong>Valerian Root </strong>is a common ingredient in many natural sleep aids. A meta-analysis of 60 studies covering a whopping 6,894 participants sought to provide solid conclusions as to whether valerian root improved sleep quality and reduced anxiety. [20] While the studies used extracts that varied in their constituents due to the extraction methods employed, the study authors conclude that “This study demonstrated that valerian could be a safe and useful herb alone and also in combination in treating sleep problems, anxiety, and associated comorbidities.” Valerian root combined with hops presents another option as a sleep remedy. [21] When compared to diphenhydramine (aka Benadryl®), the valerian-hops mixture provided a similar, mildly hypnotic effect to the drug. Study participants reported an increased quality of life at the end of the 28-day treatment compared to the placebo group. Discontinuation of the valerian-hops treatment did not cause insomnia.</p>
<p><br>These statements have not been evaluated by the Food &amp; Drug Administration. This product is not intended to diagnose, treat, cure, or prevent any disease.</p>
<p><br> <strong>References</strong><br>[1] Stamets P. (2000). <em>Growing Gourmet and Medicinal Mushrooms</em>. Berkeley, CA: Ten Speed Press.<br>[2] Sanodiya BS, Thakur GS, Baghel RK, Prasad GB, Bisen PS. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em>: a potent pharmacological macrofungus. <em>Curr Pharm Biotechnol</em>. 2009;10(8):717-742.<br>[3] Cör D, Knez Ž, Knez Hrnčič M. Antitumour, antimicrobial, antioxidant and antiacetylcholinesterase effect of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> terpenoids and polysaccharides: A review. <em>Molecules</em>. 2018;23(3):649.<br>[4] Paterson R.R.M. Ganoderma—A therapeutic fungal biofactory. <em>Phytochemistry</em>. 2006;68:1985–2001.<br>[5] Sohretoglu D, Huang S. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> polysaccharides as an anti-cancer agent. <em>Anticancer Agents Med Chem</em>. 2018;18(5):667-674.<br>[6] Zeng Q, Zhou F, Lei L, et al. <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> polysaccharides protect fibroblasts against UVB-induced photoaging. <em>Mol Med Rep</em>. 2017;15(1):111-116.<br>[7] Ali N, Muhammad A, &amp; Akbar S.A. Anxiolytic-like activity of ethanol extract of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> (Reishi) in mice. <em>International Journal of Medical Research and Health Sciences</em>. 2016;5:57-60.<br>[8] Zhao H, Zhang Q, Zhao L, Huang X, Wang J, Kang X. Spore powder of <em>Ganoderma lucidum</em> improves cancer-related fatigue in breast cancer patients undergoing endocrine therapy: A Pilot Clinical Trial. <em>Evid Based Complement Alternat Med</em>. 2012;2012:809614.<br>[9] Cavalieri E, Mariotto S, Fabrizi C, et al. alpha-Bisabolol, a nontoxic natural compound, strongly induces apoptosis in glioma cells. <em>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</em>. 2004;315(3):589-594.<br>[10] Avallone R, Zanoli P, Corsi L, Cannazza G and Baraldi M. Benzodiazepine compounds and GABA in flower heads of <em>Matricaria chamomilla</em>. <em>Phytother Res</em>. 1996;10:177-179.<br>[11] Srivastava JK, Shankar E, Gupta S. Chamomile: A herbal medicine of the past with bright future. <em>Mol Med Rep</em>. 2010;3(6):895-901.<br>[12] Shinomiya K, Inoue T, Utsu Y, et al. Hypnotic activities of chamomile and passiflora extracts in sleep-disturbed rats. <em>Biol Pharm Bull</em>. 2005;28(5):808-810.<br>[13] Amsterdam JD, Li Y, Soeller I, Rockwell K, Mao JJ and Shults J: A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial of oral <em>Matricaria recutita</em> (Chamomile) extract therapy for generalized anxiety disorder. <em>J Clin Psychopharmacol</em>. 2009;29:378-382.<br>[14] Scholey A, Gibbs A, Neale C, et al. Anti-stress effects of lemon balm-containing foods. <em>Nutrients</em>. 2014;6(11):4805-4821.<br>[15] Taiwo AE, Leite FB, Lucena GM, et al. Anxiolytic and antidepressant-like effects of <em>Melissa officinalis</em> (lemon balm) extract in rats: Influence of administration and gender. <em>Indian J Pharmacol</em>. 2012;44(2):189-192.<br>[16] Kennedy DO, Little W, Haskell CF, Scholey AB. Anxiolytic effects of a combination of <em>Melissa officinalis</em> and Valeriana officinalis during laboratory induced stress. <em>Phytother Res</em>. 2006;20(2):96-102.<br>[17] Akhondzadeh S, Naghavi HR, Vazirian M, Shayeganpour A, Rashidi H, Khani M. Passionflower in the treatment of generalized anxiety: a pilot double-blind randomized controlled trial with oxazepam. <em>J Clin Pharm Ther</em>. 2001;26(5):363-367.<br>[18] Ngan A, Conduit R. A double-blind, placebo-controlled investigation of the effects of <em>Passiflora incarnata</em> (passionflower) herbal tea on subjective sleep quality. <em>Phytother Res</em>. 2011;25(8):1153-1159.<br>[19] Janda K, Wojtkowska K, Jakubczyk K, Antoniewicz J, Skonieczna-Żydecka K. <em>Passiflora incarnata</em> in neuropsychiatric disorders-A systematic review. <em>Nutrients</em>. 2020;12(12):3894.<br>[20] Shinjyo N, Waddell G, Green J. Valerian root in treating sleep problems and associated disorders-A systematic review and meta-analysis. <em>J Evid Based Integr Med</em>. 2020;25:2515690X20967323.<br>[21] Morin CM, Koetter U, Bastien C, Ware JC, Wooten V. Valerian-hops combination and diphenhydramine for treating insomnia: a randomized placebo-controlled clinical trial. <em>Sleep</em>. 2005;28(11):1465-1471.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/best-nootropic-mushroom-extracts-for-brain-health</id>
    <published>2021-02-04T10:18:59-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-02-06T12:03:21-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/best-nootropic-mushroom-extracts-for-brain-health"/>
    <title>Best Nootropic Mushroom Extracts for Brain Health</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>By: Dr. Michele Ross </strong></p>
<p><br> <strong></strong>Feeling like your brain just isn’t working anymore? The effects of daily stress and Zoom call burnout are enough to zap your brain power and your energy. If you’re looking for a solution that won’t leave you wired and tired like slamming 4 cups of coffee will, nootropic mushrooms are for you.<br><strong></strong><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>What are nootropics?</strong><br>A nootropic is any substance that boosts brain performance. These cognitive enhancers are used to boost focus, improve memory, foster creativity, and decrease mental fatigue at work. While some nootropics are synthetic and have been made in a lab, the safest nootropics come from nature. Some of the most effective and safe nootropics are medicinal mushrooms.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Are magic mushrooms nootropic mushrooms?</strong><br>There’s been a lot of buzz about magic mushrooms, which are any mushroom that contains the active ingredient psilocybin. When used at low doses, called microdosing, these normally psychedelic mushrooms are used more in a more subtle way as a nootropic for focus and creativity. However, psilocybin mushrooms or microdosing with them remains illegal to use in most countries because they can cause hallucinogenic experiences.<br><strong></strong><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Best nootropic mushrooms</strong><br>So what are the best nootropic mushrooms then, and more importantly what are the legal nootropic mushrooms, which are ones you can buy and consume without risk of jail time. In this article, we’ll focus on the best nootropic mushrooms extracts that are safe to use and lab-tested for any impurities. The most popular and effective nootropic mushrooms include lion’s mane, cordyceps, and chaga mushrooms.<br><strong></strong><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Lion’s mane mushroom benefits</strong><br>Lion’s mane mushrooms are eaten as both a popular food and medicine in Asian countries such as China and Japan. Lion’s mane has numerous health benefits as an antioxidant and <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27481156/">anti-inflammatory</a></span>, which may help promote healthy blood flow in the brain, enhance cognitive function, and <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21383512/">reduce memory loss</a></span>. Lion’s mane mushroom contains two chemicals, erinacines and hericenones, that can stimulate the production of <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24266378/">nerve growth factor</a></span> (NGF) to promote brain cell growth and potentially <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25167134/">repair brain injury</a></span>. Finally, lion’s mane extract may promote <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29364170/">changes in the brain</a></span> that reduce the neurological effects of depression.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Cordyceps mushroom benefits</strong><br>Cordyceps mushrooms have been used in traditional Chinese medicine for centuries for everything from increasing sex drive to improving fatigue. They are packed with antioxidants that protect the brain from inflammation and <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18803231/">memory loss</a></span> due to aging. Cordyceps may even <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17827735/">boost mood</a></span>, but through a different pathway than traditional antidepressants. This is likely due to the cordyceps mushrooms containing a chemical called cordycepin that can <span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4851261/">activate AMPA receptor signaling</a></span> in the brain, improving focus and memory.<br><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Chaga mushroom benefits</strong><br>Chaga mushrooms are found naturally growing on birch trees in countries with cold weather such as Canada, Russia, and Alaska. These mushrooms have been used in traditional indigenous medicine for boosting immunity and improving overall health, but recent research suggests they have many benefits for brain health. Learning and memory may be boosted by taking chaga mushrooms due to increasing levels of the <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21779570/">neurotransmitter acetylcholine</a></span>. Chaga mushrooms contain a chemical called DBL which is a powerful antioxidant that may <span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23959789/">protect brain cells</a></span> against Parkinson’s disease or other types of cellular stress. <strong> </strong><br><strong></strong></p>
<p> </p>
<p><strong>Other herbs that support brain health</strong><br>When using medicinal mushroom extracts to support brain health, you’ll get an even bigger boost by using natural herbs that work on different pathways to improve memory, focus, and health aging. Several herbal supplements stand out as nootropics include ginkgo biloba, ashwagandha, and rhodiola rosea, which all work to reduce the negative effects of stress on the brain.</p>
<p><br>One of the easiest ways to support brain health is by taking a supplement that contains multiple nootropic mushrooms extracts and herbs. Our <span><a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/products/focus-performance">Focus Performance blend</a></span> features cordyceps and lion’s mane extracts, ashwagandha, and ginkgo biloba, intelligently formulated to help you perform at your highest level.</p>
<p>  </p>
<p><strong>References</strong></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/27481156/">International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms, Anti-Inflammatory Effects of Ethanol Extract of Lion's Mane Medicinal Mushroom, Hericium erinaceus (Agaricomycetes), in Mice with Ulcerative Colitis</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21383512/">Biomedical Research</a><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21383512/"><strong>,</strong></a><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21383512/"> Effects of Hericium erinaceus on amyloid β(25-35) peptide-induced learning and memory deficits in mice</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24266378/">International Journal of Medicinal Mushrooms, Neurotrophic properties of the Lion's mane medicinal mushroom, Hericium erinaceus (Higher Basidiomycetes) from Malaysia</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25167134/">International Journal of Molecular Science, Protective effects of Hericium erinaceus mycelium and its isolated erinacine A against ischemia-injury-induced neuronal cell death via the inhibition of iNOS/p38 MAPK and nitrotyrosine</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29364170/">International Journal of Molecular Science, Erinacine A-Enriched Hericium erinaceus Mycelium Produces Antidepressant-Like Effects through Modulating BDNF/PI3K/Akt/GSK-3β Signaling in Mice</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18803231/">Phytotherapy Research, Antiaging effect of Cordyceps sinensis extract</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/17827735/">Biological &amp; Pharmaceutical Bulletin, Antidepressant-like effect of Cordyceps sinensis in the mouse tail suspension test</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4851261/">International Journal of  Neuropsychopharmacology, 3’-Deoxyadenosine (Cordycepin) Produces a Rapid and Robust Antidepressant Effect via Enhancing Prefrontal AMPA Receptor Signaling Pathway</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21779570/">Food &amp; Function, Amelioration of scopolamine induced cognitive dysfunction and oxidative stress by Inonotus obliquus - a medicinal mushroom</a></span></p>
<p><span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/23959789/">Journal of Cellular Biochemistry, 3,4-dihydroxybenzalacetone protects against Parkinson's disease-related neurotoxin 6-OHDA through Akt/Nrf2/glutathione pathway</a></span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-benefits-of-the-reishi-mushroom</id>
    <published>2020-09-23T20:49:44-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-23T20:51:45-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-benefits-of-the-reishi-mushroom"/>
    <title>Five Benefits of the Reishi Mushroom</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Often dubbed the “elixir of long life” or “mushroom of immortality,” Reishi is one of the most potent and respected functional mushrooms on the planet...</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-benefits-of-the-reishi-mushroom">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Often dubbed the “elixir of long life” or “mushroom of immortality,” Reishi is one of the most potent and respected functional mushrooms on the planet. </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK92757/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s been used medicinally for over 2,000 years</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and contains a wonderful array of vitamins, nutrients, and compounds to support immunity and overall health. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re interested in functional mushrooms, then Reishi is one that you don’t want to miss. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Reduces Stress</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the most common uses of Reishi is for its calming, anti-stress effect.  It has shown to be effective at</span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22203880/"> <span style="font-weight: 400;">relieving anxiety and depression</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, as well as helping to</span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29519314/"> <span style="font-weight: 400;">lower blood pressure</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is thanks to the adrenal support that Reishi provides.  It’s a potent adaptogen –– i.e. a plant that helps the body deal with all kinds of physical, chemical, or biological stress.  When you’re able to relieve stress and keep your body in a state of balance, you’ll be less fatigued, have better cognitive function, and be able to maintain a sharper focus throughout the day.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As well, Reishi contains an array of different antioxidants, polysaccharides, polypeptides, triterpenes, and other compounds that work to mitigate the body’s response to stress. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you need to cool down at any point in the day, Reishi can be a great option.  That’s why it’s at the core of our <a href="/products/chill-out" style="color: #43c7f4;">Chill Out</a> blend.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Supports Immune Function</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">No matter what season of the year we’re in, it’s always important to have a well-functioning immune system.  Reishi has been clinically proven to have a</span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16230843"> <span style="font-weight: 400;">positive impact on white blood cells and the immune response</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  This leads to a powerful anti-inflammatory effect that increases your body’s ability to deal with pathogens, viruses, and stress. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Much of this effect is due to Reishi’s high concentration of beta-glucans, which have potent immune-boosting properties. </span><a href="https://www.lifeextension.com/magazine/2014/8/fight-immune-decline-with-reishi"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Reishi also promotes the development of B and T lymphocytes</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, immune cells that are vital for the production of antibodies and the overall regulation of immune function.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Anti-Cancer Properties</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cancer is one of the deadliest diseases on our planet and finding a cure has been a focus of our medical system for generations.  Functional mushrooms are beginning to show a lot of promise in their ability to help fight cancer, and Reishi is leading the charge, as the mushroom has shown to inhibit the development of cancer as well as targeting and destroying existing cancer cells.  A</span><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1734114010702528"> <span style="font-weight: 400;">2010 study</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> related Reishi’s anti-cancer effect to a compound called ganoderic acid, which is a triterpenoid found in the mushroom that attacks the development and metastasis of tumors.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">More research is needed, but the beneficial nutrients in Reishi are showing significant promise in cancer research and may be an integral part of treatment for the disease in the future. </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Reduces Inflammation</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Managing chronic inflammation in the body is essential for overall health.  Over time, inflammation damages healthy cells, tissues, and organs, and plays an important role in the development of more debilitating diseases and conditions. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The rich antioxidant profile of Reishi targets inflammation throughout the body, lowering oxidative stress and ensuring that your systems are always functioning at their best. </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Helps with Insomnia</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Part of Reishi’s potent calming effect is its ability to help you comfortably drift off to sleep every night.  Because of this, it’s a fantastic functional mushroom to add to your evening routine when you want to wind down at the end of a long day.  This is particularly the case when you’re having a hard time calming your mind before bed.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our <a href="/products/chill-out" style="color: #43c7f4;">Chill Out</a> blend is centered around Reishi and is designed exactly for this –– to help you relax and prepare for a restful night of sleep.  Head over to our <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/collections/all" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">online shop</a> to check it out. <br><br></span></p>
<p><b>References:</b></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK92757/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Ganoderma Lucidum (Lingzhi or Reishi)</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22203880/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information,Spore Powder of Ganoderma lucidum Improves Cancer-Related Fatigue in Breast Cancer Patients Undergoing Endocrine Therapy: A Pilot Clinical Trial</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/29519314/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">National Center for Biotechnology Information,Hypotensive and neurometabolic effects of intragastric Reishi (Ganoderma lucidum) administration in hypertensive ISIAH rat strain </span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16230843" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Cellular and molecular mechanisms of immuno-modulation by Ganoderma lucidum</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.lifeextension.com/magazine/2014/8/fight-immune-decline-with-reishi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Life Extension Magazine, Fight Immune Decline with Reishi </span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1734114010702528" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Science Direct,Ganoderic acid T inhibits tumor invasion in vitro and in vivo through inhibition of MMP expression </span></a></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-benefits-of-the-cordyceps-mushroom</id>
    <published>2020-09-18T14:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-24T10:42:46-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/five-benefits-of-the-cordyceps-mushroom"/>
    <title>Five Benefits of the Cordyceps Mushroom</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cordyceps has a long and rich history as a functional mushroom.  It’s native to the high mountains of China and Tibet and has been </span><a href="http://earthpulse.com/cordyceps_inc/cordyceps_story.pdf"><span style="font-weight: 400;">a staple of Traditional Chinese Medicine for centuries as a tonic to improve energy, organ function, and vitality.</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In fact, Cordyceps was so highly valued in ancient history that it was reserved for royal families.  It remains in high demand to this day for its exceptional health benefits and rarity in nature.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When it comes to functional mushrooms, Cordyceps is one of the most interesting species out there and deserves its place as a staple in modern health supplements.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are some of the most prominent health benefits of Cordyceps:</span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Increased Energy and Performance<br><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of the most prominent and well-researched effects of Cordyceps is its ability to increase energy levels and improve athletic performance.  The compound in Cordyceps that’s responsible for this is called Cordycepin.  </span><a href="https://hcpnow.com/cordyceps-boosts-energy-naturally/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">It has a notable effect on the lungs’ ability to absorb oxygen and the body’s ability to produce ATP</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> – an organic compound that provides energy to many of the processes within cells.  Studies have shown a nearly 50% increase in cellular energy levels after supplementing with Cordycepin.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Notably, in the </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3110835/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">1993 Olympics, many Chinese runners shattered world records after supplementing with Cordyceps</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">!  Whether or not you’re looking to smash any world records, Cordyceps can certainly help you improve your energy levels and physical performance whenever you need it.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our <a href="/products/energy-performance" style="color: #fdb615;">Energy Performance</a> blend is the perfect way to give yourself a reliable stream of natural energy that lasts through your toughest days.  It’s formulated to ramp your body up for optimal performance whenever you need it.  <a href="https://sporelifesciences.com/collections/all">Give it a try today and see what’s possible!</a></span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Improved Heart Health<br><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Heart disease is currently the leading cause of death in the United States, with nearly 650,000 people dying from it every year.  So, taking preventative measures to strengthen your cardiovascular system is essential for your long-term health.</span>  </p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cordyceps has shown to benefit the heart in a myriad of ways.  One of those is by helping </span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21882527/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">lower “bad” LDL cholesterol</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and </span><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21882527/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">triglyceride levels</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, which contributes to a healthier cardiovascular system.  In addition, the abundance of antioxidants and beneficial compounds in Cordyceps provide additional support for heart health and function.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<p><b>Anti-Cancer Properties</b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br>The compound </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6088102/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cordycepin has shown a remarkable ability to attack tumors and abnormal cell growths in the body</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  A recent lab test showed that Cordycepin applied to tumors resulted in them shrinking in size.  It’s currently hypothesized that supplementing with Cordyceps could help the body prevent certain cancers from even starting to form in the first place.  Cordycepin works on cancer cells by disrupting their ability to create the vital proteins they need to survive, leading to cancer cell death.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">More research on Cordyceps anti-cancer properties is needed, but supplementing with this potent functional mushroom can provide additional peace of mind in your everyday life.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Boosting Immune Function<br><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cordyceps contains an array of beneficial amino acids, vitamins, minerals, and polysaccharides that improve the body’s natural defense system.  It also provides powerful anti-fungal, anti-viral, and antibacterial properties.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With respect to the immune system, </span><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/281141441_Cordyceps_militaris_Enhances_Cell-Mediated_Immunity_in_Healthy_Korean_Men"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cordyceps helps stimulate the production of NK cells (aka Natural Killer cells)</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, which are an integral part of the immune system’s defense against pathogens, infection, and illness.  Improved immune function will benefit you whenever you cross paths with harmful invaders in the body, helping you live a long and healthy life. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<p><b>Improved Liver and Kidney Function</b><b><br></b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cordyceps is commonly used to treat kidney disease in Asian countries by helping to protect the kidneys from oxidative stress, inflammation, and improving kidney function.  </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4814030/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A 2014 study</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> found that Cordyceps achieved this by regulating the levels of metabolites that become imbalanced from chronic kidney disease (CKD), improving liver and kidney function in the process. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">In addition, Cordyceps has been shown to stimulate the liver and support detoxification processes within the body</span><b>.</b></p>
<br>
<p><b>References:</b></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="http://earthpulse.com/cordyceps_inc/cordyceps_story.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Earth Pulse, Ancient Cordyceps in the Modern World</a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://hcpnow.com/cordyceps-boosts-energy-naturally/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">HCP Now, Cordyceps Boosts Energy Naturally</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3110835/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Effect of Cs-4® (Cordyceps sinensis) on Exercise Performance in Healthy Older Subjects: A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/21882527/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Lipid-lowering effect of cordycepin (3'-deoxyadenosine) from Cordyceps militaris on hyperlipidemic hamsters and rats</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6088102/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology, Anti-tumor and anti-metastatic roles of cordycepin, one bioactive compound of Cordyceps militaris</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/281141441_Cordyceps_militaris_Enhances_Cell-Mediated_Immunity_in_Healthy_Korean_Men" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Research Gate, Cordyceps Militaris Enhances Cell-Mediated Immunity in Healthy Korean Men </span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4814030/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Cordyceps sinensis protects against liver and heart injuries in a rat model of chronic kidney disease: a metabolomic analysis</a> </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span>
</li>
</ol>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-to-improve-memory-six-natural-ways-to-boost-concentration-improve-your-focus</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:51:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-24T10:22:41-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-to-improve-memory-six-natural-ways-to-boost-concentration-improve-your-focus"/>
    <title>Six Natural Ways to Boost Concentration &amp; Improve Focus</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><b></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">An unfortunate truth about getting older is that cognitive function and memory begins to wane.  It’s a difficult transition to grapple with because in many ways your memory holds the essence of who you are.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Then, there’s the practical side of memory, things like remembering where you left your car keys, what happened in your book’s last chapter, or worse, who your family members are.  Neurological diseases can have a debilitating impact on the practical side of memory, along with your overall health and wellness, so it’s important to keep the brain healthy and properly fueled throughout life.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The good news is that there are proven natural ways to improve your memory, concentration, and focus.  If you’re keen to keep your mind sharp as a tack, keep reading.  </span></p>
<br><b>
<li>Physical Exercise<span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span>
</li>
</b>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The importance of exercise for overall health, cognitive function, and well-being cannot be overstated.  It’s absolutely essential for your body and mind.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Countless studies have shown that </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5934999/#:~:text=It%20has%20been%20showed%20that,Chang%20and%20Etnier%2C%202009)."><span style="font-weight: 400;">regular exercise improves cognitive function and working memory</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  Moreover, a </span><a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/regular-exercise-changes-brain-improve-memory-thinking-skills-201404097110"><span style="font-weight: 400;">study by the University of British Columbia</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> found that regular aerobic exercise boosts the size of the hippocampus –– the part of the brain associated with memory and learning.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Experts say to shoot for 150 minutes of moderate exercise per week, so get outside and move!</span></p>
<br><b>
<li>Meditation</li>
</b><br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many people meditate to relieve stress, calm the mind, and find peace in their daily lives, but the effects of meditation are far-reaching.  It’s a powerful practice that can have a positive impact on your physical, mental, and emotional well-being.  And the best part is, you don’t need to become a monk to reap the benefits.  In fact, </span><a href="https://theconversation.com/mindfulness-meditation-ten-minutes-a-day-improves-cognitive-function-103386#:~:text=Practising%20mindfulness%20meditation%20for%20ten,resources%20to%20do%20these%20tasks."><span style="font-weight: 400;">just 10 minutes per day will improve your concentration and working memory.</span></a><b>  </b><b><br></b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Wondering how to meditate?  You can start by just sitting comfortably in a quiet space and following your breath for ten minutes.  Every time your thoughts drift away from your breath –- and you notice –– gently bring it back into your awareness. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">You could also try using mindfulness apps like </span><a href="https://www.headspace.com/headspace-meditation-app"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Headspace</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> or </span><a href="https://www.wakingup.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Waking Up</span></a> <span style="font-weight: 400;">if you’d prefer a guided approach.  </span><b><br><br></b></p>
<b>
<li>Prioritize Your Sleep<br><br>
</li>
</b>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Research has shown that sleep is essential for memory, learning, and cognitive function.  There is a TON of processing going on in the brain while you’re asleep every night, so losing sleep is a surefire way to limit the capabilities of your brain.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While we sleep, connections between brain cells are strengthened, and memories are processed and solidified into long-term storage. </span><b><br><br></b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Getting seven to eight hours of sleep has shown to be most effective for memory recall, information processing, and overall cognitive function.  So make sleep a priority and keep your mind optimized!</span></p>
<br><b>
<li>Exercise Your Brain</li>
</b>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you don’t use it, you lose it.  Just like exercise keeps the body strong, mental exercise works wonders for cognitive ability.  This exercise can come in the form of puzzles, games, learning a musical instrument, learning a new language, creative endeavors –– anything that stimulates your mind to solve a problem or explore uncharted territory.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Exercising your brain will keep your neurons firing and keep you in peak mental condition.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<b>
<li>Spend Time in Nature</li>
</b>
<p><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nature has a powerful way of resetting our minds and reinvigorating our concentration.  So if you can, try to get outside for at least 15-20 minutes each day, preferably in a park with a lot of plant life around.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Interestingly, a </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25068481"><span style="font-weight: 400;">2014 study showed that enriching office space with plants led to improved outcomes in concentration and cognitive performance.</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  In that case, simply adding a few plants to your home or office space can be all it takes to improve your cognitive function.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<b>
<li>Include Brain-Stimulating Foods in Your Diet</li>
</b><br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The food you eat plays an important role in the health and function of your brain.  Eating a diet rich in brain-boosting foods will work wonders for your brain health and cognitive performance.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are a few foods that you should consider adding to your diet:</span></p>
<br>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<b>Omega-3’s</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">These healthy fats are essential for learning and memory and they’re abundant in fatty fish like salmon, trout, and sardines.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<b>Blueberries</b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Along with reducing inflammation and other health benefits, studies have shown that </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2850944/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">blueberries improve memory function in older adults</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span>
</li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<b>Pumpkin Seeds</b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">These are rich in magnesium, iron, zinc, and copper –– all important compounds for neurological health and brain function. </span>
</li>
</ul>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Another way to get these brain-stimulating minerals into your diet is with a robust supplement focused on cognitive performance.  Our <a href="/products/focus-performance" style="color: #f16464;">Focus Performance</a> blend features Lion’s Mane, which is a powerful functional mushroom that’s proven to improve cognitive function, focus, and memory.  It also contains Cordyceps, a functional mushroom that’s great for energy and focus, along with Ashwagandha and Ginkgo Biloba to provide you with a balanced cognitive boost whenever you need it.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Check out <a href="/products/focus-performance" style="color: #f16464;">Focus Performance</a> in our shop today and see what’s possible!</span></p>
<br>
<p><b>References:</b></p>
<ol>
<ol>
<li>
<a href="https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/regular-exercise-changes-brain-improve-memory-thinking-skills-201404097110" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Harvard Medical School, Regular Exercise Changes the Brain to Improve Memory, Thinking Skills</a> </li>
<li>
<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5934999/#:~:text=It%20has%20been%20showed%20that,Chang%20and%20Etnier%2C%202009)" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Effects of Physical Exercise on Cognitive Functioning and Wellbeing, Biological and Psychological Benefits.</a> </li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2850944/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Blueberry Supplementation Improves Memory in Older Adults. </a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2850944/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Library of Medicine, The Relative Benefits of Green Versus Lean Office Space: Three Field Experiments.</a></li>
<li>
<a href="https://theconversation.com/mindfulness-meditation-ten-minutes-a-day-improves-cognitive-function-103386#:~:text=Practising%20mindfulness%20meditation%20for%20ten,resources%20to%20do%20these%20tasks" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Conversation, Mindfulness Meditation, Ten Minutes a Day Improves Cognitive Function</a> </li>
</ol>
</ol>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/easy-ways-to-boost-your-immune-system</id>
    <published>2020-09-06T08:07:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-21T13:55:14-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/easy-ways-to-boost-your-immune-system"/>
    <title>Easy Ways to Boost Your Immune System</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The immune system is your body’s natural defense against pathogens, viruses, and bacteria, so it’s important that you keep it functioning at its best.  Immune function is based on many different lifestyle factors including age, sex, genetics, and stress levels.  The good news is that there are proven ways to improve your immune system and keep yourself protected at all times. </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Get Out and Exercise!</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Exercise is a cornerstone of a healthy lifestyle.  So, it should come as no surprise that regular, moderate exercise would improve immune function.  The data says it all –– </span><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2095254618301005"><span style="font-weight: 400;">there is a clear inverse relationship between moderate exercise training and illness risk.</span></a></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">How much exercise do you need?  Experts suggest that people should aim for a goal of 150 minutes of moderate aerobic exercise per week.  This includes activities like running, cycling, hiking, and walking.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Prioritize Your Sleep (Quality and Quantity).</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">We spend a third of our lives in bed, yet so many people neglect the importance of high-quality sleep.  </span><a href="http://healthysleep.med.harvard.edu/need-sleep/whats-in-it-for-you/health"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Getting into a regular sleep routine will work wonders for your overall health and quality of life</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  But it also keeps your immune system optimized to perform.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Studies have shown that people who don’t get enough sleep are more prone to illnesses, viruses, and disease throughout their lives.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A couple of ways to improve your sleep quality are:</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Go to bed and wake up at around the same time every day.  This helps to align your body with your natural circadian rhythm. </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Aim for seven to nine hours of sleep every night.  Less than seven hours has shown to have a detrimental effect on immune function, energy, and memory.  </span></li>
</ul>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you struggle with falling asleep –– or maintaining a restful sleep through the night –– our <a href="/products/chill-out" style="color: #43c7f4;">Chill Out</a> blend is the perfect way to wind down and the end of the day and get your body primed for relaxation.  It contains powerful ingredients like Reishi, Chamomile Extract, and Valerian root which have all been proven to relieve stress, promote relaxation, and improve sleep quality.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Stay Hydrated. </b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’re made of 60% water, so it’s no surprise that adequate water intake is necessary to keep the body functioning optimally.  Among the many functions of water in the body is carrying oxygen to the cells in the body, which keeps everything operating at its best.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Water also works to flush toxins out of the body.  You use water to wash your hands and shower every day, but we don’t often think of the internal cleansing that’s happening when you drink enough. Drinking enough water keeps bacteria and toxins from building up in your body.</span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So, how much water should you drink?  According to </span><a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/water/art-20044256#:~:text=The%20National%20Academies%20of%20Sciences,fluids%20a%20day%20for%20women"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The National Academies of Science, Engineering, and Medicine</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, adult men should drink 3.7 liters per day and adult women should drink 2.7 liters per day.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Add Functional Mushrooms to Your Routine.</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If there’s one thing functional mushrooms are great at, it’s boosting immune function.  Here are a couple of powerful options to ramp up your immune function and keep yourself protected:</span></p>
<br><b>
<li>Reishi<br><span style="font-weight: 400;">Known as the Queen of Mushrooms or Mushroom of Immortality, Reishi is a powerful adaptogen with a rich antioxidant profile to enhance immune function.  It’s renowned for its anti-inflammatory properties and its ability to stimulate white blood cell production, which are the foot soldiers of your immune system.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span>
</li>
</b><b>
<li>Turkey Tail<span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Turkey Tail has a long, valued history and is one of the most researched functional mushrooms for its immune-boosting properties, anti-cancer potential, and support for a healthy gut microbiome.  It contains an abundance of antioxidants, phenols, and polysaccharide peptide –– all of which contribute to a healthy, strong immune system.  </span>
</li>
</b><br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You can find Reishi and Turkey Tail mushrooms in our <a href="/products/protect-defend" style="color: #70bf44;">Protect + Defend</a>, <a href="/products/chill-out" style="color: #43c7f4;">Chill Out</a>, and <a href="/products/mikes-mushroom-mix" style="color: #40b6a5;">Mike's Mushroom Mix</a> blends.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>References:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2095254618301005" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Science Direct, "The Compelling Link Between Physical Activity and the Body's Defense System.  </a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="http://healthysleep.med.harvard.edu/need-sleep/whats-in-it-for-you/health" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Harvard Medical Publication, Get Sleep. </a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/in-depth/water/art-20044256#:~:text=The%20National%20Academies%20of%20Sciences,fluids%20a%20day%20for%20women" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mayo Clinic, Nutrition and Healthy Eating</a> </li>
</ol>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/mikes-story</id>
    <published>2020-09-01T04:32:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T20:30:23-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/mikes-story"/>
    <title>How Functional Mushrooms Gave Mike His Life Back</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Spore is a brand that was born out of a personal story of necessity.  It’s easy to think you’re invincible when you’re young.  But the truth is that you never know what curveballs life is going to throw at you.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our co-founder Mike had always been blessed with good health throughout his life.  He enjoyed playing a multitude of different sports, traveled to countries across the world, and lived a more-or-less carefree lifestyle.  He’d describe his active lifestyle as incredibly beneficial for his wellbeing.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mike never dealt with any major physical ailments aside from a chance injury here or there.  But he did struggle with anxiety and sleep issues for a long time.  He’d always pulled away from pharmaceutical medicines developed in a lab and looked to nature to find his healing.  Mike’s struggle with anxiety and sleep led him to natural solutions like melatonin, chamomile, and valerian root–– all of which provided relief and allowed him to continue living his life on his terms. </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By this time Mike had found his flow in life, but then it all came to a screeching halt when he was diagnosed with Multiple Sclerosis (MS) in his early 30’s.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">MS is a degenerative neurological condition that interferes with the nerve impulses within the brain, spinal cord, and optic nerves.  Although the symptoms of MS vary from person to person, most patients report coordination and balance issues, chronic fatigue, cognitive decline, and depression.  For Mike, the news of his diagnosis was devastating.  But also, a sudden and shocking wake-up call that he needed to take his health more seriously.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mike couldn’t change his diagnosis, but he did have the power over his future actions, health, and wellbeing.  The diagnosis drove Mike to commit himself to finding a safe, effective, and all-natural way to control his MS symptoms and maintain his quality of life.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Discovering Functional Mushrooms</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">After years of extensive research and experimentation, Mike discovered the immense healing potential of functional mushrooms.  Through exploring the mushroom world, Mike found natural solutions that gave him more energy, more mental clarity, and less anxiety than he’d ever felt before –– and all of this came without any hangover, come-down, or unpleasant side effects.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Once Mike realized the power of functional mushrooms to alleviate the challenges of living with MS, he was ecstatic.  They gave him back his vibrancy and lust for life and ultimately, opened up a previously unknown world of healing potential.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Now, Mike’s focused on spreading the powerful benefits of functional mushrooms to people around the world.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As a part of Spore’s mission, we actively partner and donate to organizations dedicated to the research, innovation, and development of transformative treatments for MS.  A percentage of every purchase goes toward this goal.</span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One of Spore’s most popular formulas is <a href="/products/mikes-mushroom-mix" style="color: #40b6a5;">Mike's Mushroom Mix</a> –– a well-rounded blend of vitamins, minerals, and nutrients to support your overall health.  This robust blend of 10 functional mushrooms helped Mike regain his active lifestyle and can be used to support your total body health, wellness, and vitality.  Click <a href="/products/mikes-mushroom-mix">here </a>to check it out in our shop today!</span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Together we can usher in a healthier, more vibrant world and help find a cure to MS. </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/functional-mushrooms-a-brief-overview</id>
    <published>2020-08-19T08:06:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T09:41:38-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/functional-mushrooms-a-brief-overview"/>
    <title>Functional Mushrooms:  A Brief Overview</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><b></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">When people talk about functional mushrooms, they’re not talking about your typical grocery store varieties like Portobello, Button, or Cremini.  You can save those for your omelet.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Alongside oat milk and Peloton, functional mushrooms have become one of the latest health trends, known as superfoods –– and for good reason.  Functional mushrooms have powerful health benefits and have been utilized in medicine for thousands of years.  And we’ve only just scratched the surface of their immense potential to improve our lives.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>What are Functional Mushrooms?</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Functional mushrooms are a specific subclass of mushrooms that have shown –– through clinical testing and anecdotal evidence –– to improve health, wellness, and vitality.  Many of these mushrooms have a rich history which, in some cases, dates back nearly 5,000 years.  Due to their powerful properties, functional mushrooms have been the cornerstone of countless medicinal lineages.   </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">What makes functional mushrooms unique to other mushrooms is that they’re </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4320875/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">absolutely packed with nutrients, vitamins, and minerals and have been used to treat a wide variety of health conditions and illnesses throughout history</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  Western medicine is now beginning to catch up to the ancestral knowledge that indigenous cultures around the world have utilized for generations upon generations.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><b>What are Some of the Health Benefits of Functional Mushrooms?</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The health benefits of functional mushrooms are potent and wide-ranging.  To date, clinical studies have been done on a host of different mushrooms including Lion’s Mane, Cordyceps, Reishi, and Turkey Tail.  While more human trials are necessary, preliminary trials with functional mushrooms have shown a lot of promise for </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5987239/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">regenerating nerve cells</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1160565/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">improving immune function</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5584359/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">increasing energy levels</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, and even </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4684115/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">fighting certain forms of cancer</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  These benefits span across the health spectrum because functional mushrooms contain high amounts of beneficial nutrients, vitamins, and compounds like polysaccharides, antioxidants, and polyphenols that have a positive impact across the body’s systems.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For example, a </span><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/04/150416112826.htm#:~:text=%22If%20you%20eat%20a%20shiitake,that%20the%20immune%20system%20produces.%22"><span style="font-weight: 400;">2011 study from the University of Florida</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> showed that eating just one shiitake mushroom per day for a month reduced inflammation and boosted immune function.  Talk about nutrient-dense! </span></p>
<br>
<p><a href="https://www.ecowatch.com/5-medicinal-mushrooms-1881930799.html#:~:text=Though%20some%20may%20disregard%20medicinal,mushrooms%20that%20hold%20medicinal%20benefits."><span style="font-weight: 400;">Over 35,000 species of mushrooms have shown to have some medicinal benefit</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  As far as clinical research is concerned, we’ve barely scratched the surface of the potential of mushrooms to improve the function of our body and mind.  It’s a rich and exciting research path that is now getting the traction it deserves.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><b>But What About Magic(al) Mushrooms?</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Psilocybin –– the psychoactive component of psychedelic mushrooms –– is back on researchers’ radar after showing a lot of promise as </span><a href="https://maps.org/other-psychedelic-research/211-psilocybin-research/psilocybin-studies-in-progress/1268-johns_hopkins_study_of_psilocybin_in_cancer_patients"><span style="font-weight: 400;">an effective treatment for depression and end-of-life care</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  However, don’t confuse functional mushrooms with their magical cousins!  </span><b>Functional mushrooms are NOT psychoactive.  </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Unlike psychedelic mushrooms, you can think of functional mushrooms as one of nature’s superfoods, boasting an abundance of nutrients that can have a positive impact on nearly every system in your body.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>What are the Best Ways to Take Functional Mushrooms?</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are a number of ways to incorporate functional mushrooms into your day-to-day life.  Due to difficulties with sourcing, their inedible nature, and the need for extraction, supplements are a great way to reap the benefits every day.  Just make sure that you’re buying high-quality supplements that utilize a safe method of extraction (such as water) from a reputable supplier like Spore!  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Supplements typically come in powders, capsules, or extracts –– all super easy ways to fit them into your diet.  Some functional mushrooms, like Shiitake, can be found fresh in supermarkets, so be on the lookout!  These are great to add into a stir-fry, soup, or a breakfast burrito.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Wrapping Up</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you don’t know, now you know!  Functional mushrooms have the potential to transform our understanding of human health, wellness, and longevity.  As science continues to show what’s possible, we’ll continue to share it with you!</span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Until then, we’ll keep making it easy for you to incorporate their benefits into your daily life.  You can click <a href="/collections/all">here</a> to check out our innovative blends!</span></p>
<br>
<p><b>References: </b></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4320875/" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information,  Edible Mushrooms: Improving Human Health and Promoting Quality Life</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5987239/" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Neurohealth Properties of <em>Hericium erinaceus </em>Mycella Enriched with Erinacines </span></a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1160565/" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Antiinflammatory and Immunomodulating Properties of Fungal Metabolites</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5584359/" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Altifatigue Functions and Mechanisms of Edible and Medicinal Mushrooms</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4684115/" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">National Center for Biotechnology Information, Immune Modulation From Five Major Mushrooms: Application to Integrative Oncology </span></a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/04/150416112826.htm#:~:text=%22If%20you%20eat%20a%20shiitake,that%20the%20immune%20system%20produces.%22" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Science Daily, Mushrooms Boost Immunity, Suggests Research </span></a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;"> <a href="https://www.ecowatch.com/5-medicinal-mushrooms-1881930799.html#:~:text=Though%20some%20may%20disregard%20medicinal,mushrooms%20that%20hold%20medicinal%20benefits" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ecowatch, 5 Medicinal Mushrooms</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;"><a href="https://maps.org/other-psychedelic-research/211-psilocybin-research/psilocybin-studies-in-progress/1268-johns_hopkins_study_of_psilocybin_in_cancer_patients" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">MAPS, John Hopkins Study of Psilocybin in Cancer Patients</a> </span></li>
</ol>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-to-fix-your-sleep-schedule</id>
    <published>2020-08-01T11:17:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T20:38:32-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/blog/how-to-fix-your-sleep-schedule"/>
    <title>How to Fix Your Sleep Schedule</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sleep is essential if you want to live a healthy and balanced life.  Yet in the Western world, people seem to glorify avoiding sleep as a badge of honor representing their growth, work, or otherwise.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are tons of reasons why your sleep schedule can get off track, including traveling across time zones, staying up late, excess caffeine, or watching too much Netflix before bed.  But what it all comes down to is that your internal body clock –– AKA your circadian rhythm –– is out of whack.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This isn’t something to take lightly.  </span><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6057895/#:~:text=Melatonin%2C%20the%20hormone%20produced%20by,enhanced%20restorative%20sleep%20in%20older"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Circadian rhythm issues and poor sleep quality are associated with increased risks of cardiovascular, metabolic and cognitive diseases, poor quality of life, and mortality.</span></a></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That said, there are proven ways to get yourself back on track and enjoy deep, rejuvenating sleep every night.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Avoid Blue Light Exposure Before Bed</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The light emitted from cellphones, tablets, TV screens, or computers is considered </span><a href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/articles/how-blue-light-affects-kids-sleep#:~:text=The%20blue%20light%20that's%20emitted,rhythm)%20to%20a%20later%20schedule."><span style="font-weight: 400;">‘blue light’ and interrupts your body’s natural production of melatonin at night –– an essential hormone for regulating the physiological sleep cycle</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">.  Looking at screens before bed decreases your body’s natural production of melatonin.  As a result, your circadian rhythm gets disrupted, making it harder to fall asleep and reducing overall sleep quality.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You could join the latest trendy health fad of wearing red-tinted glasses (they’re called ‘blue-light blockers) around your house at night or you could aim to avoid all blue-light emitting screens and bright lights at least one hour before bedtime.  Dimming lights around your house will also help stimulate your body to produce more melatonin and get you drifting off to sleep with ease.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Set a Specific Wake-Up Time</b></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An irregular schedule is a surefire way to disrupt your sleep schedule.  The body is designed to function best in a consistent routine.  The best way to get started with this is to pick a wake-up time that you can manage every day and </span><b>stick to it.  </b><b><br></b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s important to keep up with your wake-up time even on weekends or after late nights out.  The more consistent you are with your wake-up time, the easier it is for your body to settle into a healthy sleep routine.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Prioritize Sleep in Your Daily Routine</b><b><br></b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Preparing your body for high-quality sleep starts from the moment you wake up and continues throughout the day.  Your lifestyle can play a major role in your sleep schedule and quality.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">One thing to focus on is to expose yourself to natural light throughout the day.  Getting a healthy dose of sunlight in the morning can work wonders for regulating your circadian rhythm because it signals to your body that it’s time to wake up.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Also, be sure to keep moving!  Along with a number of other health benefits, </span><a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/wellness-and-prevention/exercising-for-better-sleep"><span style="font-weight: 400;">regular movement and exercise have shown to improve deep sleep quality.</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">  However, don’t exercise too late in the day or your body won’t have enough time to cool down before bedtime!</span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Watch What You Eat (and When You Eat It)</b></p>
<p><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Certain eating habits are notorious for disrupting sleep.  The biggest culprits are late-night snacking, caffeine, and alcohol.  Eating late at night makes it harder to fall asleep because your body still has to digest that food!  It sends the signal that you want to stay awake, not start winding down for bed.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Caffeine is a common afternoon pick-me-up, but you should avoid all caffeinated beverages after 12:00pm to keep your sleep schedule on track.  It takes several hours for the body to process caffeine and it’s notorious for disrupting the release of melatonin at night.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br></span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Last but not least, alcohol is a </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">severe </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">disruptor of sleep quality.  Still, as much as </span><a href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/articles/how-alcohol-affects-quality-and-quantity-sleep"><span style="font-weight: 400;">20% of Americans rely on alcohol to fall asleep every night</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">!  While it might make you fall asleep quickly, it does not contribute to healthy, restful sleep.  Alcohol disrupts your circadian rhythm, blocks beneficial REM sleep, and makes you wake up more frequently through the night.  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"><br><br></span></p>
<p><b>Try a Natural Sleep Supplement</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re looking for an easy way to improve your sleep quality, supplementation can be a great approach.  Taking a dose of melatonin before bed can alert your body that it’s time to start winding down for the day to prepare for sleep.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A natural way to get a similar effect is through a functional mushroom supplement or natural herbs.  At Spore, we’ve combined Reishi –– a functional mushroom with a potent calming, anti-stress effect –– and natural sleep-inducing herbs like Chamomile, Valerian Root, and Lemon Balm to help you relax and unwind at the end of the day.  Head over to our online shop and pick up our <a href="/products/chill-out" style="color: #43c7f4;">Chill Out</a> blend to give it a try!</span></p>
<br>
<p><b>Wrapping Up</b><b><br></b><b><br></b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Optimizing your sleep is essential for your overall health and wellness.  We spend a third of our lives in bed, so if your circadian rhythm isn’t aligned, it’s only going to lead to problems down the line.  Focus on your sleep now and you’ll set yourself up to live your best life for decades to come.  </span></p>
<br>
<p><b>References:</b></p>
<ol> 
<li style="font-weight: 400;">
<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6057895/#:~:text=Melatonin%2C%20the%20hormone%20produced%20by,enhanced%20restorative%20sleep%20in%20older" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">National Center for Biotechnology Information, New Perspectives on the Role of Melatonin in Human Sleep, Circadian Rhythms and Their Regulation</a> </li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/articles/how-blue-light-affects-kids-sleep#:~:text=The%20blue%20light%20that's%20emitted,rhythm)%20to%20a%20later%20schedule" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">SleepFoundation.org, How Blue Light Affects Kids &amp; Sleep</a> </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="color: #000000;"><a href="https://www.hopkinsmedicine.org/health/wellness-and-prevention/exercising-for-better-sleep" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span style="font-weight: 400;">John Hopkins Medicine, Exercising For Better Sleep </span></a></span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;"><span style="color: #000000;"> <span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.sleepfoundation.org/articles/how-alcohol-affects-quality-and-quantity-sleep" target="_blank" style="color: #000000;" rel="noopener noreferrer">SleepFoundation.org, Alcohol and Sleep</a>  </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span> </span></li>
</ol>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
