<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients.atom"/>
  <title>Spore Life Sciences - Meet Our Ingredients</title>
  <updated>2020-09-10T10:02:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Spore Life Sciences</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/valerian-root</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T10:02:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:15:01-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/valerian-root"/>
    <title>Valerian Root</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Valerian has a long history dating back to ancient Greece, where doctors Hippocrates and Dioscorides often prescribed it as a sleep aid.  Today it’s widely recognized as a powerful medicinal herb that’s commonly used to promote relaxation, reduce anxiety, treat digestive disorders, and improve overall sleep quality.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/turmeric</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:59:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T09:20:16-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/turmeric"/>
    <title>Turmeric</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Native to South Asia, Turmeric is a potent anti-inflammatory, anti-bacterial, and antioxidant that’s one of the most important herbs in Ayurvedic medicine.  Its active ingredient, curcumin, has shown to aid in the management of oxidative and inflammatory conditions, metabolic conditions, arthritis, and anxiety.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/turkey-tail</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:56:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T09:17:49-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/turkey-tail"/>
    <title>Turkey Tail</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Turkey Tail has a long, valued history and is one of the most researched functional mushrooms for its immune-boosting properties, anti-cancer potential, and support for a healthy gut microbiome.  It contains high concentrations of protein-bound polysaccharides, which work to activate and inhibit specific immune cells and decrease inflammation throughout the body]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/shiitake</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:48:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T09:17:07-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/shiitake"/>
    <title>Shiitake</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[With a history dating back over 100 million years, Shiitake mushrooms have long been a staple of Asian cuisines.  Shiitake is anti-inflammatory and packed with nutrients to strengthen your immune system, support heart health, and control blood sugar levels.  It’s also unique to the world of fungi because it contains all eight essential amino acids.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/reishi</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:34:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-16T19:19:09-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/reishi"/>
    <title>Reishi</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Known as the Queen of Mushrooms or Mushroom of Immortality, Reishi is a powerful adaptogen with a rich antioxidant profile.  It’s history dates back at least 2,000 years, where Chinese healers used it to treat a wide range of health conditions.  Reishi is known to enhance immune function and is a potent stress-reliever, flooding the body and mind with tranquility.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/passion-flower</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:31:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:14:11-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/passion-flower"/>
    <title>Passion Flower</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[A perennial vine native to North America, Passion Flower has been used historically to treat anxiety, stress, and insomnia.  Its unusual blossoms have a long history of use as a traditional medicine in Native American cultures, which was later adopted by European settlers.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/panax-ginseng</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:30:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:07:25-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/panax-ginseng"/>
    <title>Panax Ginseng</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[According to ancient Chinese medicine, Panax Ginseng is known for strengthening Qi (vital life force), organ support, and increasing knowledge.  It’s a common supplement in herbal medicine today, used notably to increase energy levels, boost libido, lower blood sugar, and balance mood.  To this day it remains the most popular herbal remedy in East Asia.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/maitake</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:27:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:05:35-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/maitake"/>
    <title>Maitake</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Loaded with beneficial polysaccharides, triterpenes, and bioactive chemicals, Maitake is an impressive adaptogen that provides superb immune-boosting power and a natural dose of energy.  This mushroom was once so highly valued in Japan that it was known as the ‘Dancing Mushroom’ because commoners would dance for joy when they found it.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/lion-s-mane</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:15:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:08:58-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/lion-s-mane"/>
    <title>Lion’s Mane</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[One of the most renowned medicinal mushrooms, Lion’s Mane is a potent cognitive enhancer that contains a plethora of beneficial compounds to improve working memory, mental clarity and acuity, and overall brain health.  Studies have also shown Lion’s Mane to be effective at protecting against dementia, reducing symptoms of anxiety and depression, and helping repair nerve damage.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/lemon-balm</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:09:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:13:27-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/lemon-balm"/>
    <title>Lemon Balm</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[A mild sedative with mood-balancing properties, Lemon Balm is an excellent lemon-scented herb for people who struggle to wind down and relax at the end of the day.  It also has a strong anti-inflammatory effect and has shown promise in reducing blood sugar levels in people with diabetes.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/king-trumpets</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T09:01:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:02:13-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/king-trumpets"/>
    <title>King Trumpets</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Native to the Mediterranean regions of Europe, Africa, and the Middle East, King Trumpets are loaded with antioxidants and are an excellent source of magnesium, zinc, and vitamin B6.  They contain an important amino acid called ergothioneine which works to cleanse vulnerable areas of the body like the liver and kidneys, making King Trumpets a fantastic mushroom for your immune system and total body health.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/guarana</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:58:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:06:46-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/guarana"/>
    <title>Guarana</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[The Guarana vine is home to the Amazon Rainforest, where indigenous cultures have long taken advantage of its stimulating properties. It is now a staple of energy supplements that reduces mental fatigue, provides sustained natural energy, and also contains many potent antioxidants for immune support.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/green-tea-extract</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:52:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:06:12-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/green-tea-extract"/>
    <title>Green Tea Extract</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Green tea has been used medicinally in Japan and China for thousands of years.  High in antioxidants, vitamins, and beneficial compounds, Green Tea Extract increases your energy levels while supporting overall health, mental alertness, and immune function.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/ginkgo-biloba</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:48:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:10:29-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/ginkgo-biloba"/>
    <title>Ginkgo Biloba</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[The Gingko tree is one of the oldest surviving tree species in the world, dating back more than 200 million years.  Gingko Biloba improves cognitive function and cardiovascular health, while flushing toxins from the body.  It’s rich with antioxidants and has been used traditionally to treat blood disorders, enhance circulation, and improve memory.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/cordyceps</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:43:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:03:36-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/cordyceps"/>
    <title>Cordyceps</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[A rare mushroom native to the high mountains of China and Tibet, Cordyceps is a powerhouse for energy production, immune function, and organ health.  It’s used extensively in ancient Chinese medicine.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/chamomile</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:41:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:12:17-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/chamomile"/>
    <title>Chamomile</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[An ancient medicinal herb, Chamomile is a potent anti-inflammatory and mild sedative that relieves stress, promotes calmness, and supports healthy digestive function.  Egyptians considered Chamomile to be a sacred plant, believing it was a gift from the God of the Sun.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/chaga</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:38:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T09:10:31-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/chaga"/>
    <title>Chaga</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Used for centuries to support longevity, immunity, and overall health, Chaga reduces inflammation, prevents disease, and helps regulate blood sugar and cholesterol.  Chaga’s fruiting bodies are loaded with polysaccharides which have proven to support immune function and overall health.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/ashwagandha</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:35:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-17T11:09:37-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/ashwagandha"/>
    <title>Ashwagandha</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[A staple of Ayurvedic medicine for thousands of years, Ashwagandha is a powerful adaptogen that reduces stress, supports heart health, and maintains balance in the body.  It’s native to the Indian sub-continent and is considered to be a grounding herb that promotes longevity, vitality, and happiness.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/antrodia</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T08:31:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-14T20:55:44-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/antrodia"/>
    <title>Antrodia</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Known as the ‘Fungus of Fortune’ in Taiwan, Antrodia is used to support liver and heart health.  It also contains a variety of immune-boosting components to fortify your body’s natural defense system.  Antrodia is a common therapeutic ingredient in traditional Chinese medicine and has been used to treat a variety of conditions including stomach issues, hypertension, inflammation, and diabetes.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/agarikon</id>
    <published>2020-09-10T04:10:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2020-09-15T09:08:25-04:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://sporelifesciences.com/blogs/ingredients/agarikon"/>
    <title>Agarikon</title>
    <author>
      <name>Alex Kaplunov</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[Called ‘the elixir of long life’ by the Greek physician Dioscorides in 65 A.D., Agarikon has proven anti-viral, anti-microbial, and anti-inflammatory properties that attack the host bacteria of numerous diseases and conditions.  This mushroom can grow for up to 100 years and is revered for its exceptional defense against invading pathogens.]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
